<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Narrative_models]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Narrative_models</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:32 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Tasks]]></title><description><![CDATA[In scopewhere i left offmight discardKeep main goals in mind when I get distracted!!
Lit review Find&nbsp;different&nbsp;(macrostructure-based) narrative&nbsp;models&nbsp;
Find&nbsp;their target&nbsp;purpose&nbsp;= ~50% What&nbsp;type of&nbsp;research&nbsp;topics,&nbsp;practical&nbsp;use?&nbsp;
Target cultures/languages&nbsp;covered?&nbsp; Collect&nbsp;their&nbsp;terms&nbsp;&amp;&nbsp;definitions&nbsp;= ~75% Use lit review to&nbsp;create&nbsp;an annotation&nbsp;schema&nbsp;for&nbsp;kirikou&nbsp;film and&nbsp;retellings&nbsp; Find&nbsp;what&nbsp;schema&nbsp;are&nbsp;used&nbsp;in&nbsp;different&nbsp;projects&nbsp;
Propose working schema&nbsp; Lit review as prep for annotation is complete when I have notes for all these.
The rest is bonus -- some of it can be used for upcoming article, some is out-of-scope but helps me think anyway. I have to limit time spent on out-of-scope so it doesn't make in-scope priority task lag.Media studies
Propp, Greimas, etc. = French/Russian formalists: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://sci-hub.ru/https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139522502.005" target="_self">https://sci-hub.ru/https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139522502.005</a> Campbell's Monomyth Some crit in Attebery 2014 Three-act structure
Freitag's pyramid
Act (Scene-&gt;Sequel loops)
World lit incl. oral lit
Kwik kwak (Caribbean)
Griot (West Africa)
Robleto (Nicaragua)
East-asian four-act Chinese (poetry): qi cheng zhuan
Korea: gi seung jeon gyeol
Japan: kishotenketsu Jo-ha-kyu (beginning, break, rapid)
Chiastic structure (symmetry in structure)
...<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_story_structures" target="_self">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_story_structures</a>
Check Katya's notes to figure out how they interface with all thisThink about where to put:
models for monolingual VS multilingual populations = seems to start with ENNI-&gt;MAIN?
Adapting narrative structure to African context + identifying episode boundaries
Check Nikitina Episodes. (Very relevant, took notes)
Check Nikitina Greek. (Not relevant, doesn't discuss episodes)
Check Nikitina Ep's sources: Labov 1972 Tomlin 1987
Fox 1987
Bakker 1993
van Dijk 1981
Mithun 2002
Schiffrin 1981 Look for more sources about ep boundaries Ji 2002
Abu-Akel 1999 MAIN:
identify primary sources for revised model: gagarina et al 2019, what else? then check &amp; correct notes.
check later research for annotation: see paper on Afrikaans, Xhosa
how does MAIN annotate into episodes?
Trabasso &amp; Nickels:
how do they annotate into episodes?
Find how to host notesOrganize source database:
add tags
sources from Frog email
scattered sources in Later research + Story grammar
Zotero ??Think about where to put:
narrative structure in media studies + from other cultures = parallel to model filliation?
]]></description><link>tasks.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Tasks.canvas</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:14:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Thinking out loud]]></title><description><![CDATA[... Cont from notes for Ji 2002:-&gt; Take any utterance
-&gt; It contains multiple cues that allow multiple interpretations (let's say: can interpret as signalling discourse unit shift, or non-shift)
-&gt; You need a critical mass of cues getting the same interpretation (eg they all have an interpretation that matches with "discourse unit now shifting") for discourse structure to emerge, for the producer AND receiver of utterance.
-&gt; Discourse structure is constantly co-constructed &amp; negotiated.
--- It breaks down when there is too much mismatch in the inventory of cues and in their selected interpretation (? leading to a drop below critical mass; I mean mismatch between producer &amp; receiver);
--- It stays operational when mismatches stay under a certain threshold + matches stay above critical mass;
--- "Broken discourse" can be repaired, and "operational discourse units" get maintained, shifted or broken (by producer + receiver!) as interaction unfolds.Some of this is reinventing-the-wheel &amp; fuzzy.
I can revisit it when I've read more about pragmatics.
The point is that studying discourse unit requires pragmatic valuation from multiple perspectives. Single perspective has serious conceptual limitations. Single perspective seems common in study of narrative in linguistics &amp; applied linguistics, because few connections are made with pragmatics, semiotics, lit studies, all of which pay attention to interpretation.What's the relation between Narrative structure &amp; Culture?
Cross-cultural pragmatics studies this without falling into essentializing/universalist traps.
There is a relation but it's always mediated by multiple types of identity + it's about local community of practice, not distant scales like ethnicity/nation/etc.What's the relation between Narrative structure (narrative units; episode boundaries) &amp; Interpretation (of expressions as signaling shift in episode)
Interaction: see interactional approaches to narrative described in Defina &amp; Johnstone 2015
Stance: Du Bois 2007 + Spronck 2020What's the relation between Narrative structure &amp; Discourse structure?
To what degree does it reduce to changes in Frame?
Current thinking: Discourse units emerge through pragmatic valuation from multiple perspectives(/interaction participants). As in, concordant valuation of enough signs to reach a critical mass, which license?perform? the discourse unit, sort of. etc etcbasic inventory of a narration:
setting: place + time + social context. (+ mental landscape)
plot: initial event + complication + outcome
characters = participants
narrator = perspective
Initiating event + Reaction &amp; actions = Changes in world state
Setting = initial world state
Outcome = non-initial world state
Half-baked but there's something there.Backgrounding vs foregrounding; continuity vs discontinuity
Return to this after reading/thinking about semantics.]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/thinking-out-loud.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Thinking out loud.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:10:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[* Start here]]></title><description><![CDATA[I think that an analysis of narrative structure grounded in recent theory ideally integrates some, or ideally all of these approaches:
interactional linguistics
cross-cultural pragmatics; discourse studies (intersects with pragmatics); semantics
(?information structure, Frame)
(?dialogic/construction grammar -- probably not this project)
The narrative structure models I've studied so far seem very disconnected from recent theory.
The model we adopt has a direct impact on how narrative structures are annotated (categories, but more importantly process).
I've started to read about pragmatics/semantics to pitch ideas for an updated model.Looking at how these models coded their data does not seem very useful to us; it's incompletely described, and it's not an example of good practices.
I think a better alternative is to look into recent publications about best practices for linguistic annotation, like: Handbook of Linguistic Annotation (general reference; book)
Hoek &amp; Scholman 2017 (focuses on discourse; article)
Best practices would impact the workflow, the labels used, and the description given in our writing.
Learning about best practices can also be used to quality-check past annotations (&amp; correct/re-do, or just learn from it for future projects). Episode boundaries are sensitive to some types of expressions/functions; distribution is different at +start of ep VS -start of ep.
The forms populating the distribution are language-specific; so something like "nouns are overrepresented at the start of ep" is a falsified claim. That's true for some languages, and the opposite is true for others.
What's comparable across languages is: that there are similar distribution patterns (pure stats) + that there's a shared set of "types of expressions/functions sensitive to ep boundary" + that it organizes around a binary (+- start of ep).
Types of expressions/functions sensitive to EP boundary
We can propose additions to the list of types of expressions/functions sensitive to ep boundary she presented.
We can reframe it more clearly with a split between function &amp; potential forms = semantics/pragmatics VS syntax/lexicon, roughly.
(More speculative: maybe some elements ought to be removed from the inventory as spurious correlation that has to do with working memory.)
Ji 2002 identifies these variables as salient indicators of episode boundaries. Meaning, when given the task to place episode boundaries, research participants highly agree in case of (+) conditions, and agree a lot less in case of (-) conditions.
The study was conducted in just one language (English), but it builds an inventory of functions &amp; form types, rather than language-specific forms.
+- Marked sentence
+- Discontinuity in time, space
+- Discontinuity in theme, if it has an additional feature: +- New participant
+- Anaphor
==(non-participant theme with no callback = adds little-to-no episode boundary salience, for example.) +- Major discontinuity (any type)
I wonder why theme did not receive further, more precise split.
Anaphor is significant beyond 'theme discontinuity'; most obviously 'referring expression (pron vs NP)'. Compare "linking construction".
('Marked sentence' + Anaphor -&gt; information structure) linguaculture: "culture manifested through language use" (p.5) linguacultures vary within and between languages; the point of "linguaculture" is to make a small claim, connected to a community of practice speech acts: typology of speech acts from Edmondson &amp; House 1981 p.107
they warn against proliferation of new types of speech act; better to identify subtypes than new types expression: "lexical items of various complexity" (p.73) tertium comparationis: "A common quality in two entities to be compared, which is the basis of the comparison." (p.260); nb different types of stable variables possible principle of comparability standard situation: "The notion of a standard situation involves participants’ rather fixed expectations and perceptions of social role. Role relations are transparent and predetermined, the requester has a right, the requestee an obligation, the degree of imposition involved in the request is low, as is the perceived degree of difficulty in realizing it. In a nutshell, the participants know where and who they are. Clearly, the distinction between a standard and a nonstandard situation is not clear cut." (p.76)
language use in standard situation can be studied in one linguaculture, then compared with another/several
they exclude study of language use in non-standard situations, and idiosyncratic uses ritual VS conventionalization, ritual frame, RFIE (ritual frame-indicating expression) ... ancillary methodology vs comparative methodology: ancillary methods are exploratory pilot studies
comparative methods (in cross-cultural pragmatics) = compare use of expressions in standard situation in at least 2 linguacultures discourse gambit linking constructions (type of gambit): see p.144 + their source: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://benjamins.com/catalog/target.27.3.03hou" target="_self">https://benjamins.com/catalog/target.27.3.03hou</a> types of talk Multidisciplinary Introduction to Discourse_chapter: Narrative in Everyday LifeScope of narrative
Narrative and time
Narrative point of view and plot structure
beginning, middle, end
setting: place + time + social context. (+ mental landscape)
"complication", "initiating event", etc.: event that disrupts equilibrium of the ordinary
"psychological responses and actions"
"outcome"
//Ok so some division with 3 units is established in multiple disciplines. I'm wondering to what extent we need something special called "narrative structure". is it superfluous? is it 90% generic semantics/discourse structure + 10% conventions for content &amp; interpretation?//
Building a narrative
p.77 "The audience is a co-author of narrative form and meaning."
Introduction
Discourse &amp; Cognition
Discourse pragmatics
Discourse, grammar and interaction
Conversation analysis: An approach to the analysis of social interaction
Discourse and culture
Based on naturalistic data (from English-speaking white american families, so NB limitations)
"narrators in conversational setting interactionally create narratives by recruiting discourse skills that are most readily available to them"
//I find this paper insightful because it considers both language use &amp; cognitive use (whereas eg story grammar focuses on cognitive representation, per the author). This captures the importance of interpretation in discourse structure.//Episode boundaries = Points where an episode starts
Start of episode:
Over-representation of NP //English-specific//
New Macroproposition //More generalizable idea//
This bit jumps out:
"macropropositions do not set up an episode boundary, rather they set up a subunit within the master episode. They are considered part of the master episode since they maintain the thematic/topical continuity of it"
Continuity vs discontinuity has a lot to do with how episodes connect, whether you go up or down in structure as story unfolds. Would be great to search for recent publications that follow up on this.Schiffrin 1981 (on tense/aspect):
p.52 "Thus, finding no narratives told entirely in the HP, she concludes that it is not the HP per se which is a dramatic device in narrative, but the switch. The tendency for verbs in one tense to cluster together is given a functional, discourse-level explanation: maintenance of one tense groups events into one scene or episode, while switching separates events from one another." //The key idea is "switch" or "pair".
What makes up the pair depends on multiple factors (temporal perspective adopted, TAMP system of the language, etc.), but it's always a pair.//Labov 1972:
p.363:
"Fully formed narrative may show the following:
Abstract
Orientation
Complicating event
Evaluation
Result or resolution
Coda"
This publication adds a narrative unit, relative to Labov &amp; Waletzky 1967
It has more definitions and explanations of terms
see Defina &amp; Johnstone 2015 pp.153-154 for mise en contexte of + terms from Labov 1972
Worth reading/thinking about more closely, the narrative units presented are heterogenous in a way that bothers me (plot units vs units giving explicit interpretation grid?).
Need to return to this
Mithun 2002 (on nominalization)
p.58-61 Nominalized sentences for backgrounding information
"The speaker steps out of the narrative or other account to offer side comments, background description, explanation, evaluation, or other supplementary commentary. The nominalization of independent clauses provides an important rhetorical device for adding texture to discourse, separating the main event line or sequential points in a discussion from side commentary."
//Compare to nominalization + backgrounding particles in Wan, and particles 'and', 'already', converbs in Chuvash.
Maybe read more about: backgrounding vs foregrounding. This is in the domain of information structure. Also NB it's the only category Nikitina presents without a pair for -Start of unit.//Tomlin 1987
p.455: Focus/foregrounding!
p.457: "First, the critical theoretical linguistic notions, — paragraph, episode, and focus, — are weakly defined and generally resistant to empirical analysis. Second, and not independent of the first weakness, the practical identification of such notions in genuine text data depends on relativistic thematic notions of relevance and salience, which are similarly vague at the present moment (van Dijk and Kintsch 1983:171; but see also Tomlin 1984, 1985)"
p.457-458: Comprehension strategies &amp; production strategies don't have to be the same
p.458 Macroproposition
p.461 Proposition
...
p.472: Shift in attention during discourse production
p.475: "The primary drawback to the episode/paragraph approach lies in the dif ficulty of providing explicit and structure-independent means of identifying episodes and episode boundaries. In this study episodes are argued to be a function of attention allocation, and episode boundaries are identified and manipulated independently of text structure and without dependence on introspection. It may even suggest that in the end discourse units, like the paragraph, are more likely to be the artifacts of linguistic analysis than they are cognitive units utilized by speakers in discourse production"
Need to return to this, very perceptive.Fox 1987 (NP/pron anaphora)<br>
(chapter starts here: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="tomlin1987.pdf > page=166" data-href="tomlin1987.pdf#page=166" href="episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/tomlin1987.html#page=166" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">tomlin1987, p.157</a>)
p.157-158: distance, ambiguity, thematic continuity
p.167-172: Pron vs NP, looks at some problem with just analyzing use in terms of linear distance + nuances of NP/pron distribution
Need to return to thisVan Dijk 1981
...Bakker 1993
Boundaries, Topics and the Structure of discourse
Discontinuity of participants and events
Perspectival discontinuity]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/*-start-here.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/* Start here.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:05:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[tomlin1987]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/tomlin1987.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/sources from Nikitina 20XX/tomlin1987.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 13:53:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[schiffrin1981]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/schiffrin1981.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/sources from Nikitina 20XX/schiffrin1981.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 12:41:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Abu-Akel 1999]]></title><description><![CDATA[Based on naturalistic data (from English-speaking white american families, so NB limitations)
"narrators in conversational setting interactionally create narratives by recruiting discourse skills that are most readily available to them"
//I find this paper insightful because it considers both language use &amp; cognitive use (whereas eg story grammar focuses on cognitive representation, per the author). This captures the importance of interpretation in discourse structure.//Episode boundaries = Points where an episode starts
Start of episode:
Over-representation of NP //English-specific//
New Macroproposition //More generalizable idea//
This bit jumps out:
"macropropositions do not set up an episode boundary, rather they set up a subunit within the master episode. They are considered part of the master episode since they maintain the thematic/topical continuity of it"
Continuity vs discontinuity has a lot to do with how episodes connect, whether you go up or down in structure as story unfolds. Would be great to search for recent publications that follow up on this.p.439: "those ones which serve to establish local cohesive ties (e.g. anaphora, definite reference), and those which mark overarching structural relationships (e.g. summary statements, pronominal/nominal shifts) in a text (Hinds, 1977)."
p.441: "an episode is defined as a unit of narrative production, subsumed in the flow of interaction and information processing."p.441-442 "Both linguistic and conceptual/cognitive coordinates are simultaneously operated by narrators to demarcate episodic boundaries. This marking is manifested on three levels: the macroproposition; the use of anaphora and other linguistic markers; and the establishment of conceptual frames."
p.442 "Second, the transition between macropropositions represents episode boundaries, irrespective of the transition inducer (distraction, interruption, shift in attention or whatever), and is often marked by expressions (such as full NPs and temporal markers) denoting changes in time, place, scenery, participant, perspective, possible world, and so forth."
p.442 "boundaries of episodes can be marked by the introduction of what Andersen (1999) calls ‘frames’. ""
p.442 "The analysis of the data shows that narrators in conversational narratives employ certain distinct discourse features to denote the beginning of an episode. These features are manifested at both the macro-level, i.e. the use of macropropositions, and the micro-level, i.e. the use of linguistic devices such as anaphora, inceptive and temporal markers."p.444 NP vs pron (less so when eg narrating about self -&gt; 1st person pron, no NP counterpart)
p.445 "it is possible to use a full definite NP or a proper noun within a discourse segment, in our case an episode, not necessarily to indicate the instantiation of a new episode, but rather to ‘convey some additional information, i.e., lead the hearer or reader to draw additional inferences’ (Grosz et al., 1995: 216) - that is, to create a specific discourse effect, or to minimize misunderstandings due to ambiguity in referencing."
short-term memory decayp.447 "The new macropropositions form new frames that include new agents or topics often combined with times (denoted by temporal markers) and places (denoted by locatives). A new macroproposition is set up as soon as propositions are interpreted that no longer fit the macroproposition of the previous episode (Van Dijk, 1982). "
p.447 "That is, a new macroproposition of a subsequent episode is set up either at the completion of the previous episode, when the current episode is interrupted (say, due to a shift in attention of either the storyteller or the listener), or when narrators move into the present"p.448-450 Interruptions
p.449 "The multi-layered nature of macropropositions (Van Dijk, 1982) results in cases where macropropositions do not set up an episode boundary, rather they set up a subunit within the master episode. They are considered part of the master episode since they maintain the thematic/topical continuity of it"]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/abu-akel-1999.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Abu-Akel 1999.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 12:38:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[abu-akel1999]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/abu-akel1999.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/abu-akel1999.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 12:24:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Source database]]></title><description><![CDATA[Attempt at collecting all the sources, ongoing.see also <a data-href="Story grammar_Primary and synthesis" href="narrative-models/2_story-grammar/story-grammar_primary-and-synthesis.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"><span class="iconize-icon-in-link" title="LiCheckSmall" aria-label="LiCheckSmall" data-icon="LiCheckSmall" aria-hidden="true" style="transform: translateY(20%);"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" class="check-small"><path d="M12 21C16.9707 21 21 16.9707 21 12C21 7.0293 16.9707 3 12 3C7.0293 3 3 7.0293 3 12C3 16.9707 7.0293 21 12 21Z"></path><path d="M7.5 12.5L10.5 15.5L16 10"></path></svg></span>Story grammar_Primary and synthesis</a>see also Later research notes
<br><a data-href="Berman &amp; Slobin_Later research" href="narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_later-research.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"><span class="iconize-icon-in-link" title="LiCheckSmall" aria-label="LiCheckSmall" data-icon="LiCheckSmall" aria-hidden="true" style="transform: translateY(20%);"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" class="check-small"><path d="M12 21C16.9707 21 21 16.9707 21 12C21 7.0293 16.9707 3 12 3C7.0293 3 3 7.0293 3 12C3 16.9707 7.0293 21 12 21Z"></path><path d="M7.5 12.5L10.5 15.5L16 10"></path></svg></span>Berman &amp; Slobin_Later research</a>
etc.
]]></description><link>source-database.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Source database.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 11:49:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Source roundup]]></title><description><![CDATA[Ji 2002
Does not cite Abu-Akel 1999
Linguistics (Pragmatics)Bamberg &amp; Marchman 1990
quoted in Ji 2002
LinguisticsMiall 2004. Can't download. LINK
Based on russian formalism (Reformatsky 1992) and other sources
Some connection with story grammar: cites Haberlandt et al 1980
Literary studiesAbu-Akel 1999
This is about Np vs Pronouns, but also macropropositions (discourse unit connected to Frame). I can reevaluaate relevance when I know more about pragmatics.
Linguistics (Discourse studies, pragmatics)Same book
Tomlin 1987
"... - difficulty of providing explicit and structure-independent means of identifying episodes and episode boundaries"
Fox 1987
ep boundary, noun vs pronounLabov 1972
criteria for narrative analysisVan Djik 1981
"criteria for thematic unity"; ep boundarySchiffrin 1981
ep boundary, choice of tense-aspectBakker 1993
ep boundary, conj &amp; discourse particlesMithun 2002
ep boundary, backgrounding eg nominalizationNarrative &lt;-&gt; Discourse, Pragmatic
Fina &amp; Johnstone 2015Linguistic annotation -&gt; Annotation of discourse units
General: Handbook of linguistic annotation
Discourse: Hoek &amp; Scholman 2017Cross-cultural pragmatics
House &amp; Kadar 2021Chatman 2019
Story and Discourse: Narrative Structure in Fiction and Film
NB that's a whole book
Film &amp; lit studiesSpeech act theory &amp; literature (Intersection of Pragmatics &amp; Narrative studies):
Miller 2002 (Book)
Rabinowitz 1995 (article) - <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://sci-hub.ru/https://doi.org/10.1017/CHOL9780521300131.014" target="_self">https://sci-hub.ru/https://doi.org/10.1017/CHOL9780521300131.014</a>
Bollobas 1980 (Article)<br>
I want to find where Discourse (in the sense of pragmatics) intersects with Literature. -&gt; "Discourse analysis" + "Narrative" = Fina &amp; Johstone 2015! <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://sci-hub.ru/https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118584194.ch7" target="_self">https://sci-hub.ru/https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118584194.ch7</a><br>Lg-internal pragmatic variation <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0378216624001450" target="_self">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0378216624001450</a>]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/source-roundup.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Source roundup.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 13:42:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hoek Scholman 2017]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/hoek-scholman-2017.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Hoek Scholman 2017.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 13:42:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[van djik 1981]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/van-djik-1981.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/sources from Nikitina 20XX/van djik 1981.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 13:32:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Original sources]]></title><description><![CDATA[
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Gagarina%20et%20al%202012&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Bf4ca0616-b4ae-4966-8408-979919791ea3%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Gagarina et al 2012</a>&nbsp;_ MAIN (presentation&nbsp;of the&nbsp;method&nbsp;&amp; design&nbsp;behind&nbsp;it = unrevised version) / Background,&nbsp;models&nbsp;and&nbsp;terms, source&nbsp;mining
Gagarina &amp; Bohnacker 2019 introduces the revised model; Revised materials &amp; transcription procedure are online <br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844" target="_self">https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844</a> Benchmark:
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Gagarina%20et%20al%202019&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Ba9fc09b6-5323-4c7c-beea-493aced102ff%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Gagarina et al 2019</a>&nbsp;- German,&nbsp;Russian,&nbsp;Swedish;&nbsp;adults&nbsp;/&nbsp;Monolingual&nbsp;research, background, cultural variation,&nbsp;theory&nbsp;
Metastudy:
Lindgren et al 2019 _ MAIN (review&nbsp;of&nbsp;studies&nbsp;on&nbsp;multilingual&nbsp;children) /&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research
]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_original-sources.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Original sources.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:53:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Coding schema]]></title><description><![CDATA[Transcription rules are very explicit &amp; precise (see <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Transcription_rules.pdf" data-href="Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Transcription_rules.pdf" href="narrative-models/5_main/main_transcription_rules.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">MAIN_Transcription_rules</a>), probably informed by conversation analysis.
Annotation procedure much less so.
Description of annotation is given in: <br>Gagarina et al 2012_MAIN <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="gagarina-et-al2012_MAIN.pdf > page=19" data-href="gagarina-et-al2012_MAIN.pdf#page=19" href="narrative-models/5_main/gagarina-et-al2012_main.html#page=19" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">p.13</a>: Westby's decision tree shown as guide to code episodes. Gagarina et al 2019_MAIN_Adult p.197-198: This article lists the categories, without describing the process. Multiple coders with high agreement.
Lindgren Bohnacker 2022 p.492: This article lists the coding categories, without describing the process.
Klopp &amp; Smith 2025 p.181-182: Coding of macrostructure relies on Westby's decision tree. Data labelled as "no sequence" receive an additional label: description, or action. Two coders, with high agreement. No description of process beyond that.<br>
Started looking for an annotated dataset on MAIN's website. Could continue: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://zenodo.org/records/4724970#.Yf1qqKbMK5d" target="_self">https://zenodo.org/records/4724970#.Yf1qqKbMK5d</a>
They have a standard annotation procedure that produces high agreement between codes. It's practical for their purpose, but flawed theory-wise. Checked other sources to see if I could find a more recent &amp; comprehensive annotation procedure; I did not find anything of the sort.
Gagarina &amp; Bohnacker 2019_MAIN-revised
Lindgren et al 2019
<br>Full package of MAIN documents on website; Transcription Rules does not touch on annotation. See <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844" target="_self">https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844</a>
Old notesExamples of score rubric shown in Gagarina et al 2012: 67-86
One score rubric created per story
The score rubric has more or less items depending on the complexity &amp; length of the story.Here's a rough adaptation:The rubric also tracks:
Quantified version of "Structural complexity" Nb of AO sequences
Nb of G (no AO) sequences
Nb of GA / GO sequence
Nb of GAO sequences Nb of internal state terms (total and nb by type)
When adapting this protocol for labelling data, quantification of structural complexity can flow directly from coding data with macrostructure categories.
]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:52:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Klopp Smith 2025 Afrikaans Xhosa]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/klopp-smith-2025-afrikaans-xhosa.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Klopp Smith 2025 Afrikaans Xhosa.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:30:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Transcription_rules]]></title><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_transcription_rules.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Transcription_rules.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:28:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Transcription_rules]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/main_transcription_rules.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/MAIN_Transcription_rules.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:20:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[lindgren-bohnacker2022_german_swedish]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/lindgren-bohnacker2022_german_swedish.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/lindgren-bohnacker2022_german_swedish.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:16:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[gagarina-et-al2019_MAIN_adult]]></title><link>narrative-models/5_main/gagarina-et-al2019_main_adult.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/gagarina-et-al2019_MAIN_adult.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:04:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Next]]></title><description><![CDATA[Their narrative model was designed for cross-cultural applicability, and revised based on observed differences. It's precise &amp; suitable for comparative research.
The main weakness is that it's built around a very specific method/purpose (storyboard elicitation + diagnostic evaluation of children), which creates cultural bias, even despite the explicit effort to increase cross-cultural applicability, because SLP diagnosis only takes place in a subset of societies (Rich/Industrialized to some degree).Another possible flaw is that I don't think it's grounded in cross-cultural pragmatics, or pragmatics/interactional linguistics.]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_next.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Next.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Method]]></title><description><![CDATA[Storyboard elicitation. Set of four stories presented through a sequence of 6 pictures. These stories were designed directly for MAIN. They are controlled for complexity, and cross-cultural appropriateness.Data collected from children &amp; adults (adults serve as benchmarks for children)
Multiple languages/cultures; monolingual and multilingual]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:44:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Later research]]></title><description><![CDATA[Partial list:
Lindgren &amp;&nbsp;Bohnacker&nbsp;2022 _ German,&nbsp;Swedish&nbsp;/&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Tribushinina,&nbsp;Irmawati&nbsp;&amp; Mak 2022 _&nbsp;Indonesian, Dutch /&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Bohnacker, Lindgren &amp;&nbsp;Öztekin&nbsp;2022 _ Turkish,&nbsp;Swedish&nbsp;/&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Fiani, Henry &amp; Prévost 2022 _&nbsp;Lebanese&nbsp;Arabic, French /&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;&nbsp;
Fichman&nbsp;&amp; al 2022 _&nbsp;Russian,&nbsp;Hebrew&nbsp;/&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Kosutar&nbsp;et al 2022 _&nbsp;Croatian&nbsp;/&nbsp;Monolingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Lindgren 2019 _&nbsp;Swedish&nbsp;/&nbsp;Monolingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Klop&nbsp;&amp; Smith 2025 _ Afrikaans, Xhosa
See also: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/publications/" target="_self">https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/publications/</a>
<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/projects/" target="_self">https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/projects/</a>
]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_later-research.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Later research.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Diagnostic evaluation
Language acquisition, cross-linguistic comparisonIts main purpose is to screen for language impairments among bilingual children, and monolingual children, with the same protocol.]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:41:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Diagnostic evaluation]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:39:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Next]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare with MAIN: development of tools for same purpose as ENNI, for monolingual and multilingual populations]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_next.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Next.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:39:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Method]]></title><description><![CDATA[Storyboard elicitation, set of stories designed for the protocol
Children
Monolingual, English]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:37:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Later research]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Abdalla, Mahfoudhi Alhudhainah 2020 - Kuwaiti Arabic / Monolingual research, models and terms, cultural variation Lee 2013 – Korean / Monolingual research Could find more research of this type ]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_later-research.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Later research.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Language acquisition
Cross-linguistic research; comparative linguistics]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare with Trabasso &amp; Nickels
Narrative structure gets demoted in B&amp;S]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Language acquisition
Discourse analysis
Cognitive research]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Story grammar]]></title><description><![CDATA[There are several story grammar models from the 70-80s. Stein &amp; Glenn's seems like the most influential from this period. Coding: Variable and dependent on the purpose. For evaluation of skill = use of a score rubric, giving points based on presence of elements from the model. For research = transcription of data, label speech units (utterances or other) with categories from the model. Coding procedure &amp; schema are incompletely described by contemporary standards.
In later research based on Story Grammar, labeling an idiosyncratic set of categories drawn from multiple models seems common. Secondary sources:
Lang2003 (ch12 of Narrative Intelligence): pp.199-200 on background; example of story grammar used in AI research Works based on a synthesis:
Abdalla, Mahfoudhi Alhudhainah 2020 - Kuwaiti Arabic / Monolingual research, models and terms, cultural variation
Tappe &amp; Hara 2013 _ Chichewa / Background, multilingual research, models and terms Cites Stein &amp; Glenn, unclear if based on synthesis:
Soodla &amp; Kikas 2010 - Estonian / Monolingual research Todo list of other story grammar models
? Todo find research based on story grammar other than Stein &amp; Glenn ]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/story-grammar.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/Story grammar.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:26:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Story grammar_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Variable from the start. Study narrative structure itself
Study narrative structure in order to research cognitive mechanisms (linguistic comprehension), cognitive development.
Language acquisition
Story grammar models were adapted to serve purposes other than those originally considered:
Evaluation of narrative skill as diagnostic tool (close to original purpose)
Refinement of AI language models ]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/story-grammar_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/Story grammar_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn__Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[Stein &amp; Glenn in contextOperationalized model of Stein &amp; Glenn 1979Narrative modelEvaluating whole models: does it suit...Research participants demographicsSetting(Other episodes, or sets)ResponseEpisodeStoryCompare w Labov &amp; Waletzky
Situate in story grammar models from the 70sStein &amp; Glenn_BackgroundRelevance todayAdults?Speakers with mature lg skills?Monolingual speakers?Western, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?Internal responsePlan sequenceInitiating eventMultilingual speakers?Internal planOther cultures and languages, which?Other methods?Wider range of purpose?Children?Speakers with developing lg skills?Plan applicationResolutionDirect consequencesReactionResearch on cognitive development and language acquisitionStein &amp; Glenn_PurposeChildren listen to a spoken story, then recall &amp; retell it (p.75)
Stories were adapted for the experiment (p.74)Children
Single language/culture (American English)Stein &amp; Glenn_MethodAttemptEpisode systemCompare w Trabasso &amp; Nickels: model reduced to minimal set of categoriesStein &amp; Glenn_NextInternal system:
First&nbsp;element&nbsp;(enabler) = (1)
Second&nbsp;element&nbsp;and/or top&nbsp;category = (2)&nbsp;
Some&nbsp;elements&nbsp;can&nbsp;appear&nbsp;out of the&nbsp;sequence&nbsp;they&nbsp;present&nbsp;(p.67).&nbsp;
Stein &amp; Glenn_TermsIncomplete description (it's a single paragraph on p.88).
Data is given a score; no full transcription, no systematic data labelling.Roughly corresponds to:An excellent idea they had was to create story schemas for each story (p.84-87), and use that as reference for the coding.Stein &amp; Glenn_Coding schemaStein &amp;&nbsp;Glenn's&nbsp;model&nbsp;is&nbsp;the story&nbsp;grammar&nbsp;model&nbsp;from&nbsp;the 70-80s&nbsp;that&nbsp;gets&nbsp;cited&nbsp;the&nbsp;most. It's extremely granular. It focuses on modeling underlying stories, rather than narrations of stories. (It's the same distinction as deep syntax with nesting, empty categories,... vs surface-only.)This confused me for a bit: the actual model used when citing Stein &amp; Glenn is not theirs; it's a synthesis, most similar to Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992.Stein &amp; Glenn_Short descriptionOriginal source: Stein &amp; Glenn 1979(Secondary sources)]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn__map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn__Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:11:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels__Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[Trabasso &amp; Nickels in contextOperationalized model of Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992Narrative modelEvaluating whole models: does it suit...EpisodeResearch participants demographicsCore; GAOEventInternal responseGoalBerman 1988
Trabasso &amp; al 1989 (discourse analysis)Compare with Stein &amp; GlennTrabasso &amp; Nickels_BackgroundOriginal source:
Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992(Secondary sources)Short descriptionAttemptRelevance todayThe description of the coding schema is incomplete. This is a reconstruction based on their examples of transcripts (p.257, 263) and schemas (p.255, 256, 262), as well as their analysis (p.268-269).Transcription was divided in:
Set of clauses narrating the same picture (p.257)
Subdivided in clauses (p.254, 257)
Labelled data was used to create causal network schemas.Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Coding schemaOutcome(Incomplete GAO = non-GAO unit)Adults?Compare with Berman &amp; SlobinTrabasso &amp; Nickels_NextChildren?Other methods?Speakers with mature lg skills?Speakers with developing lg skills?Wider range of purpose?Few definitions, a lot of paraphrasing + deduction necessary. Some terms are hopefully(?!) defined in Trabasso et al 1989.
Abbreviations included because they directly connect terms &amp; coding schema.p.253 First paragraph explains that all units can enable units of the same kind, not just next unit in causal sequence. "Events can (...) cause other events, (...) Goals can motivate goals (...)"Trabasso &amp; Nickels_TermsLanguage acquisition
Discourse analysis
Cognitive researchTrabasso &amp; Nickels_PurposeSettingStoryboard elicitation (Frog, Where Are You?)
Data collected from children and adults
Single language/culture (American English)Trabasso &amp; Nickels_MethodOther cultures and languages, which?Western, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?Monolingual speakers?Multilingual speakers?]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels__map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels__Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:10:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Research on cognitive development and language acquisition]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Next]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare w Trabasso &amp; Nickels: model reduced to minimal set of categories]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_next.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Next.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Method]]></title><description><![CDATA[Children listen to a spoken story, then recall &amp; retell it (p.75)
Stories were adapted for the experiment (p.74)Children
Single language/culture (American English)]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[gagarina-bohnacker2019_MAIN-revised]]></title><link>narrative-models/5_main/gagarina-bohnacker2019_main-revised.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/gagarina-bohnacker2019_MAIN-revised.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 10:57:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ling-annotation-handbook]]></title><link>ling-annotation-handbook.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ling-annotation-handbook.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:29:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ji 2002]]></title><description><![CDATA[p.1257: Episode transitions are defined by major changes in time, space, and/or theme.
When the content of a narrative lack such changes (absent, or change is not major), the episode boundary is less clear.p.1259-1960. This study builds on:
Chafe (1979, 1980 = Pear story data), re types of discontinuity
Prideaux &amp; Hogan (1993) + Givon (1993), re marked sentence structures
p.1262: Discontinuity tends to be introduced by marked structures. The study was conducted in English, so marked structure = sentence with any of these sentence-initially:
AdvP
PrepP
ParticipP
NounP
SubordinateP
Types of discontinuities labelled &amp; quantified (p.1262-1263):
Temporal discontinuity
Spatial discontinuity
Thematic discontinuity (new theme or participant*. + NO explicit link with previous elements. //No data of this type in any group, see p. 1262 + 1266.//)
Thematic reorientation (type of thematic discontinuity = new theme or participant. + THERE IS explicit link with previous elements)
(Thematic discontinuity vs reorientation = p.1265)
* Participant means character in story.
Author divided data in three groups representing rates of agreement;
Group 1: &gt;70% (p.1261)
Group 2: 40-69% (p.1265)
Group 3: 1-39% (p.1265)(p.1261-1265) There is a high rate (&gt; 70%) of agreement between research subjects, re: episode boundaries, when: there is a major change in time, place and/or theme, AND when there is a marked structure.
Regarding theme, agreement stays high when: new theme is a participant (p.1264);
or there is an anaphor (callback to previous element; what they define as "thematic reorientation") (p.1265). //Looking further: Anaphora in group 1 all introduce "larger unit" or new participant + have a marked structure.//
(p.1266-1269) Rate of agreement re episode boundaries drops in these conditions.
(p.1266-1267) When there are less marked sentence structures (group 1 had 80% whereas group 2 had 41% and group 3 had 50%);
When thematic reorientation has either of these properties: (p.1267) When new NON-PARTICIPANT theme is introduced, regardless of whether the sentence structure is marked. (Seen in group 2 &amp; 3.)
(p.1268) When new theme introduction starts a small unit (group 3), agreement drop is larger than when it "initiates a larger unit" (group 2). //No further explanation included; examples supporting the statement are on p.1267+1268. I think this is about shifting between episodes 'on same level' vs shifting between those 'on different levels'.// (p.1268) When the discontinuity (of any type; time-space-theme) is not major. (Author calls these "local".)
So, according to this study, the variables that make episode boundaries more or less salient are:
+- Marked sentence
+- Discontinuity in time, space
+- Discontinuity in theme, only with additional features: +- New participant
+- Anaphor
(so non-participant theme with no callback = adds very little episode boundary salience, for example. NB Why not split Theme further &amp; more precisely? + Anaphor is meaningful for the structure beyond this, at minimum in terms of NP vs Pron, what else?) +- Major discontinuity (any type)
//There's a lot to unpack re discontinuity of theme
First: what's happening would be clearer with precise, labelled splitting of theme. The problem is how you do you split it, and how do you justify your split? I can think of: participant VS internal state VS dialogue VS packaged action/event.
Second: Anaphor is meaningful outside thematic discontinuity. Most obviously regarding NP/pronouns to refer to participants. Also in some cases of discontinuity in time or place (less sure about that). The problem is that switch between anaphor &amp; non-anaphor has multiple triggers (eg memory decay), and anaphor can be distant or local. Switches are a cue for ep boundary, yet there are switches within episodes, and non-switches across episodes.
... (Rest of reflection in <a data-href="Thinking out loud" href="episode-boundaries/thinking-out-loud.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Thinking out loud</a>.)
//(p.1269) "The episode seems to be perceived by language users mainly as a unit of events or actions" //-- This explains why new non-participant theme &amp; non-major discontinuity can get perceived as indicating episode shift and not indicating episode shift; because they don't impose a new "event-action unit", essentially.//Source/claim miningp.1258:
"It has also been established that narrative is not composed merely of sequences of sentences, but is hierarchically organized into intermediate units such as episodes or paragraphs (Bamberg and Marchman, 1991; Black and Bower, 1979; van Dijk, 1982; Grimes, 1975; Hinds, 1977, 1979; Longacre, 1979; Pu, Prideaux, and Stanford, 1992; Tomlin, 1987."p.1259:
"Empirical support for the validity of episodes has been provided by psycholinguistic studies which indicate that people recalling stories treat information of an episode as an integral unit (cf. Black and Bower, 1979; Glenn, 1978; Mandler, 1978; Thorndyke, 1977), a result which is further supported by studies that have found the episode-shift effect, i.e., readers pause longer in processing episode-initial sentences that introduce an episode shift than they do for episode-internal sentences (Haberlandt, Berian, and Sandson, 1980; Mandler and Goodman, 1982)"p.1264:
"Many researchers have proposed that the default assumption of readers is that the order in which the events are reported corresponds to the chronological order of these events (e.g., Comrie, 1985; Dowty, 1986; Fleischman, 1990; Givon, 1992; Hopper, 1979). This has been called the iconicity assumption (Fleischman, 1990; Hopper, 1979)."]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/ji-2002.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Ji 2002.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 14:36:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[van dijk 1981]]></title><description><![CDATA[//Van Dijk is foundational in pragmatics re "macrostructure" vs "microstructure".
Also seems co-foundational with Stein &amp; Glenn re: using "episode" as internal unit of narrative//p.179 Intuitive notions of 'episode'
p.180-183 The semantics of episodes
p.183-190 Analysis of an example: A news story.//I need to learn about what cross-cultural pragmatics does with these notions.//]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/van-dijk-1981.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/van dijk 1981.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[defina & johnstone 2015]]></title><description><![CDATA[p.153-155 Structural approaches to Narrative (1950s-1980s)
Russian formalists + Claude Lévi-Strauss = structuralist approaches to Narrative
Taken up in American linguistics &amp; literary theory of the 1960s
Linguistic approaches to narrative:
Labov &amp; Waletzky 1967, 1997 + Labov 1972
Becker 1979. Javanese shadow-theater plots
//Early cross-cultural pragmatics!// Chafe 1980b. Compares production of spoken story from wordless film, in different languages.
Clancy 1980. Japanese VS English use of nominals when introducing characters
Tannen 1980. Greek vs American narration of same film; cultural differences Linguists in 1980s revisiting myths &amp; folktales collected by earlier ethnographers: Hymes 1981
Chafe 1980a
Sherzer 1982
Tedlock 1983
Woodbury 1987
//NB connect with sources provided by Frog// Van Dijk &amp; Kintsch 1978, van Dijk 1977, 1980: Explicit model for story production &amp; comprehension involving macrostructure, macrorules //Van Dijk's work integrates ideology later on, connecting to Narrative turn//
"Story grammar" models. //same objective as Van Dijk but different subfield (language acquisition &amp; applied linguistics cluster, more or less)//
p.155-158 Interactional approaches to Narrative
//SUPER relevant, will return to this//p.158-159 Narrative in Sociocultural Practice
//Early study of intralingual variation in English//
Heath 1982, 1983: Study on two working-class family's children, one white &amp; one african-american. Different conceptions of what's a good story -&gt; White: factual tale with a moral VS African-american: entertaining, fantastic tale.
//...Then there's study of other languages too, sometimes comparative. Whether the studies cited are monolingual or multilingual is not always clear.//
American vs Israeli
Anglo-american vs Puerto Rican
etc.''This work on the uses of narratives in the lives of particular groups has contributed to a recent shift away from the project of linking narrative structures and functions to predefined demographic differences such as gender, nationality, or ethnicity, and toward a more nuanced view of storytelling as a type of practice embedded within other practices that define particular communities describable only through ethnography (see De Fina and Georgakopoulou 2011: 73–5)."
//This is really important. Can't speak of monoliths like "West" or "Africa". Connects to idea like "look locally".//p.159 //NB diverse types of narratives:
narratives in court
police interviews
asylum-seeking procedures
interviews
news stories//
p.159-160 The Narrative Turn across Disciplines (1970s-2000s)
"Narrative has come to seem important to people throughout the humanities and social sciences"
History -&gt; New Historicism
Psychology
Sociology
Anthropology
Education
...
//I think this corresponds to transition from structuralist to postmodern, involving Critical Discourse Analysis outside linguistics. -&gt; connects to Foucault, Bourdieu, etc.; ideology//
]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/defina-&amp;-johnstone-2015.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/defina &amp; johnstone 2015.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 14:28:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[defina & johnstone2015]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/defina-&amp;-johnstone2015.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/defina &amp; johnstone2015.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 14:11:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[du bois 2007]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/du-bois-2007.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/du bois 2007.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 13:16:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[bakker1993]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/bakker1993.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/sources from Nikitina 20XX/bakker1993.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 12:10:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[labov1972]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/labov1972.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/sources from Nikitina 20XX/labov1972.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 12:10:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[mithun2002]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/sources-from-nikitina-20xx/mithun2002.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/sources from Nikitina 20XX/mithun2002.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 12:10:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nikitina 20XX Episodes]]></title><description><![CDATA[When identifying episode boundaries:
Per Nikitina, the distribution of forms is sensitive to +-Start of unit.
The forms populating the distribution are language-specific
What is stable across languages is: (1) which form types are sensitive, (2) the fact that there's a binary contrasts between start and non-start, (3) the rough distribution
(1) Form types
Word frequency Adverb types
Verbs
(Word frequency overall) Other Referring expressions
Backgrounding
Tense/aspect (2) Start vs non-start
//What about end signaling? Is there any? That's a question for next readings.//(3) Rough distribution
NB My understanding of stats &amp; distribution is naive, but this is what I understood.
Distribution is similar overall whatever the forms concerned. Eg similar distribution of Wan past-perfect and Chuvash past-perfect.
OTOH, in some cases, it is not, &amp; then it must be explained in terms of grammatical difference. Eg pro-drop lg VS non-prop-drop lg = noun VS pronouns do not have comparable distribution across languages.
//There's more to say about 'Expected vs exceptional distribution -&gt; impact on theory'. (Like, exceptional distribution without responsible grammatical difference -&gt; theory needs adjustment. (1) What's expected vs exceptional distribution? That's a stats question. (2) Adjustment how? Need a clearer working theory to explore that.)//
Fox 1987 + Tomlin 1987 are chapters from same book = Tomlin (ed.) 1987]]></description><link>episode-boundaries/nikitina-20xx-episodes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Nikitina 20XX Episodes.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ji2002]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/ji2002.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/ji2002.pdf</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 10:03:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Later research]]></title><description><![CDATA[NB these sources have a variable level of engagement with Berman &amp; Slobin; what they have in common is the method.Works based on the same method, macrostructure:
Rungrojsuwan 2019 Thai / Monolingual research
Shunhua-Tianlong2023 Mandarin Chinese / Monolingual research Works based on the same method, microstructure
Klamer Moro 2020 Alorese, Teiwa (two languages of indonesia) / Monolingual research
Brown 2004 Tzeltal / Monolingual research
Bennett Kastor 2002 Irish + English bilinguals / Multilingual research, microstructure
Bavin 2000 WarlpiriTable of&nbsp;studies&nbsp;using&nbsp;Frog&nbsp;story on&nbsp;languages&nbsp;of&nbsp;Africa&nbsp;OverallConvergence relative to source:
Purpose: lang acq
Method: same method has been used abundantly before &amp; afterDivergence relative to source:
Purpose: lang description]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_later-research.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Later research.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Terms]]></title><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 14:47:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Terms]]></title><description><![CDATA[For now, I focused on collecting macrostructure terms. I did not find definitions, everything is paraphrased/deduced.There are a lot more terms:
?? maybe for microstructure and micro-macro interface in part IV pp.389-59X
for lg-specific categories in part III pp. XXX-XXX.
For the upcoming project, a closer look at terms (+ definition + coding) from these chapters might be useful:
pp.389-39X: Form-Function Relations in the Development of Narrative
pp.393-45X: Temporal Relations in Narrative: Simultaneity
Macrostructure seems to get little use in the analysis; microstructure (language-specific forms) get most of the attention. ]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Terms]]></title><description><![CDATA[Few definitions, a lot of paraphrasing + deduction necessary. Some terms are hopefully(?!) defined in Trabasso et al 1989.
Abbreviations included because they directly connect terms &amp; coding schema.p.253 First paragraph explains that all units can enable units of the same kind, not just next unit in causal sequence. "Events can (...) cause other events, (...) Goals can motivate goals (...)"]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Terms]]></title><description><![CDATA[Terms and def. taken from Gagarina et al 2019 (revised model)
I may find more later, there's scattering in between initial &amp; revised model (3 publications or more)]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 14:46:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Later research]]></title><description><![CDATA[Publications; purpose + participant demographicsSome&nbsp;engagement&nbsp;with&nbsp;Labov in&nbsp;these&nbsp;articles:&nbsp;
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Nicolas%20%20Ntuli%202025&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Bb391e7be-c9d1-403f-974a-6c3694a1d1e8%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Nicolas&nbsp; Ntuli 2025</a>&nbsp;-- uses L&amp;W&nbsp;categories&nbsp;for&nbsp;its&nbsp;coding&nbsp;
Rungrojsuwan&nbsp;2019&nbsp;&nbsp;
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Shunhua-Tianlong2023&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Bbdf8ec2e-b2c1-4675-ac25-aad358e6e016%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Shunhua-Tianlong2023</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;
Todo&nbsp;find&nbsp;more&nbsp;research&nbsp;of&nbsp;this&nbsp;type&nbsp;Converges how, relative to source?(TBC)
Terms, definitions, coding schemas (partial)
Purpose (lang acq, variationist description)Diverges how, relative to source?(TBC)
Method
Terms, definitions and coding schemas (partial)
Purpose (? discourse studies ?)]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_later-research.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Later research.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Story grammar_Primary and synthesis]]></title><description><![CDATA[(Don't know where I mined this)Late 70s story grammar models:
Mandler &amp; Johnson 1977
Rumelhart 1975
Stein &amp; Glenn 1979
Thorndyke 1977
(etc.?)90s synthesis models:
Trabasso &amp; al 1992
Anderson &amp; Evans 1996(Mined from gagarina et al 2019: 192-193)
Primary sources (70s-80s):
Labov 1972
Labov &amp; Waletzky 1967
Mandler &amp; Johnson 1977
Peterson &amp; McCabe 1983
Stein &amp; Glenn 1979
Stein &amp; Policastro 1984
Synthesis with GAO:
Stein &amp; Policastro 1984
Trabasso &amp; Nickes 1992
Trabasso et al 1992
Westby 2012
]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/story-grammar_primary-and-synthesis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/Story grammar_Primary and synthesis.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bamberg Marchman 1990]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/bamberg-marchman-1990.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Bamberg Marchman 1990.pdf</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 13:51:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cohn2012]]></title><link>article-notes/cohn2012.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Cohn2012.pdf</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 13:51:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Ep boundaries]]></title><description><![CDATA[Episode as a working memory during production: p.272-273p.260 Extracting Episodic Structures
Example of "complete" episode: event, goal, attempt, outcome, reaction
Example of a "well-formed" episode: two events, goal, attempt, successful outcome -- all with causal relation
Example of "basic" episodes: goal, attempt, outcome
p.264-265 Episodic Structures
Two types of unit: episode (contains GAO), and non-GAO unit (not an episode; "consists of a clause or a set of clauses that maintain a topic but does not allow the inference of a goal")
I assume they proceeded more or less like this: Look at each clause; attribute "function of clause", and "level". (I assume these must be coding tiers.) Eg first clause is "event", "level 1".
(1) Review all functions: Spot local GAO sequences = these are episodes. Sort categories other than GAO (event, setting, IRC = internal state) into the identified episodes. In my example, clauses given the function G3-A-O form an episode, all at level 3.
(2) Review again. Look for distant GAO sequences (with intervening level change) = these are also episodes. An episode must be able to count as a narrative unit within another episode; otherwise there would be no larger episodes, they would always have a unit missing. This could be solved with an extra tier "function of episode".
Whatever remains belongs to no episodes = counts as non-GAO unit. <img alt="tb1992_262 1.png" src="article-notes/images/tb1992_262-1.png" target="_self"><br>
<img alt="tb1992_262 2.png" src="article-notes/images/tb1992_262-2.png" target="_self">There are no appendices or examples of annotated data in text.Figures, for context.(1a) Their causal network captures how narrative categories can connect.
(1b) It captures how episodes connect through goal hierarchy.
(4) See how a network based on frog story data is similar to their 1b figure.<br>
<img alt="tb1992_252.png" src="article-notes/images/tb1992_252.png" target="_self"><br>
<img alt="tb1992_262.png" src="article-notes/images/tb1992_262.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_ep-boundaries.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Ep boundaries.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 13:13:30 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[tb1992_262 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/tb1992_262-2.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/tb1992_262-2.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/tb1992_262 2.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:57:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[tb1992_262 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/tb1992_262-1.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/tb1992_262-1.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/tb1992_262 1.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:51:50 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[tb1992_252]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/tb1992_252.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/tb1992_252.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/tb1992_252.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 11:39:25 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[tb1992_262]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/tb1992_262.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/tb1992_262.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/tb1992_262.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 11:39:25 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Coding schema]]></title><description><![CDATA[The description of the coding schema is incomplete. This is a reconstruction based on their examples of transcripts (p.257, 263) and schemas (p.255, 256, 262), as well as their analysis (p.268-269).Transcription was divided in:
Set of clauses narrating the same picture (p.257)
Subdivided in clauses (p.254, 257)
Labelled data was used to create causal network schemas.]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nikitina20XX_episodes]]></title><link>episode-boundaries/nikitina20xx_episodes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Episode boundaries/Nikitina20XX_episodes.pdf</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 13:04:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nikitina2013_greek]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/nikitina2013_greek.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Nikitina2013_greek.pdf</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 13:04:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Coding schema]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is a reconstruction!
The coding schema is described in depth in Chapter I-B (pp.25-28).
I checked App II: Glossing &amp; Transcription in case it might provide more details about coding schema; it doesn't but NB! p.660 definition of clause as unit of transcription.
The description is incomplete. More can be reconstructed by looking through analytical chapters (I started but then discontinued this task); see <a data-href="Berman &amp; Slobin_Terms" href="narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_terms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"><span class="iconize-icon-in-link" title="LiAlertCircle" aria-label="LiAlertCircle" data-icon="LiAlertCircle" aria-hidden="true" style="transform: translateY(20%);"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" class="lucide-alert-circle"><circle cx="12" cy="12" r="10"></circle><line x1="12" y1="8" x2="12" y2="12"></line><line x1="12" y1="16" x2="12.01" y2="16"></line></svg></span>Berman &amp; Slobin_Terms</a>
Much of the coding is not deployed in the analysis (p.27), which makes it impossible to fully reconstruct.
Transcription is divided into clauses.All clauses are&nbsp;labelled.
Some&nbsp;words (mostly verbs)&nbsp;are&nbsp;labelled&nbsp;when&nbsp;they&nbsp;fit certain&nbsp;categories.Coding&nbsp;was&nbsp;not made&nbsp;through&nbsp;a standard&nbsp;method&nbsp;used&nbsp;in all&nbsp;languages.&nbsp;&nbsp;
Rather, it&nbsp;was&nbsp;split&nbsp;into&nbsp;(1)&nbsp;analyzing&nbsp;forms&nbsp;= lg-specific, (2)&nbsp;analyzing&nbsp;functions&nbsp;= applicable&nbsp;across&nbsp;languages, hence lg-neutral.pp.85-106: categories from Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992 (-&gt; Trabasso et al 1989, Stein &amp; Glenn 1979) are used to model the stimulus story "Frog where are you", and for the coding schema for narrations of "Frog where are you" collected before B&amp;S 1994]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI__Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[ENNI in contextOperationalized model of ENNINarrative modelEvaluating whole models: does it suit...Later research based on ENNIEpisodeResearch participants demographicsCoreSettingReactionInitiating EventCompare with Berman &amp; SlobinENNI_BackgroundShort descriptionDiagnostic evaluationENNI_PurposeGoalAttemptOutcomeInternal responseENNI_TermsLater research converges how, relative to source?
Abdalla, Mahfoudhi Alhudhainah 2020 - Kuwaiti Arabic / Monolingual research, models and terms, cultural variation Lee 2013 – Korean / Monolingual research Could find more research of this type ENNI_Later researchLater research diverges how, relative to source?Storyboard elicitation, set of stories designed for the protocol
Children
Monolingual, EnglishENNI_MethodOriginal source:
Schneider 2006(Secondary sources)Compare with MAIN: development of tools for same purpose as ENNI, for monolingual and multilingual populationsENNI_NextTranscription is divided into "communication units, each of which consisted either of (1) one independent clause plus any dependent clauses associated with it, or (2) of a sentence fragment".Tellings are given a score, rather than coded, same as MAIN (?? is there a purpose-dependent splie like MAIN actually??).
The scoring procedure is described (p. 230-231) + examples shown in Appendix (final page).ENNI_Coding schemaRelevance todayWestern, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?Other cultures and languages, which?Speakers with developing lg skills?Multilingual speakers?Children?Other methods?Adults?Speakers with mature lg skills?Monolingual speakers?Wider range of purpose?Different types of narratives?]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni__map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI__Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 11:33:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin__Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[Berman &amp; Slobin in contextOperationalized model of Berman &amp; Slobin 1994Evaluating whole models: does it suit...Later research based on Berman &amp; Slobin 1994Narrative modelResearch participants demographicsEvent componentsPlot componentsCompare with Trabasso &amp; Nickels
Narrative structure gets demoted in B&amp;SBerman &amp; Slobin_BackgroundStoryboard elicitation (Frog, Where Are You?)
Data collected from children. ? ADULTS (probably included too?
Multiple language/cultures (English, Spanish, German, Hebrew, Turkish); monolingualThere are many studies based on eliciting retellings of the Frog story (1979). Some of them analyze narrative macrostructure.
Most studies focus on microstructure, not macrostructure.
Findings from this type of study are limited, because it's a single story and not designed to control for complexity or cultural appropriateness like MAIN.
Frog story studies are often done on minority languages, and they represent a highly diverse set of languages/cultures. Berman &amp; Slobin_MethodShort descriptionFor now, I focused on collecting macrostructure terms. I did not find definitions, everything is paraphrased/deduced.There are a lot more terms:
?? maybe for microstructure and micro-macro interface in part IV pp.389-59X
for lg-specific categories in part III pp. XXX-XXX.
For the upcoming project, a closer look at terms (+ definition + coding) from these chapters might be useful:
pp.389-39X: Form-Function Relations in the Development of Narrative
pp.393-45X: Temporal Relations in Narrative: Simultaneity
Macrostructure seems to get little use in the analysis; microstructure (language-specific forms) get most of the attention. Berman &amp; Slobin_TermsOriginal source:
Berman &amp; Slobin 1994(Secondary sources)This is a reconstruction!
The coding schema is described in depth in Chapter I-B (pp.25-28).
I checked App II: Glossing &amp; Transcription in case it might provide more details about coding schema; it doesn't but NB! p.660 definition of clause as unit of transcription.
The description is incomplete. More can be reconstructed by looking through analytical chapters (I started but then discontinued this task); see <a data-href="Berman &amp; Slobin_Terms" href="narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_terms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow"><span class="iconize-icon-in-link" title="LiAlertCircle" aria-label="LiAlertCircle" data-icon="LiAlertCircle" aria-hidden="true" style="transform: translateY(20%);"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" class="lucide-alert-circle"><circle cx="12" cy="12" r="10"></circle><line x1="12" y1="8" x2="12" y2="12"></line><line x1="12" y1="16" x2="12.01" y2="16"></line></svg></span>Berman &amp; Slobin_Terms</a>
Much of the coding is not deployed in the analysis (p.27), which makes it impossible to fully reconstruct.
Transcription is divided into clauses.All clauses are&nbsp;labelled.
Some&nbsp;words (mostly verbs)&nbsp;are&nbsp;labelled&nbsp;when&nbsp;they&nbsp;fit certain&nbsp;categories.Coding&nbsp;was&nbsp;not made&nbsp;through&nbsp;a standard&nbsp;method&nbsp;used&nbsp;in all&nbsp;languages.&nbsp;&nbsp;
Rather, it&nbsp;was&nbsp;split&nbsp;into&nbsp;(1)&nbsp;analyzing&nbsp;forms&nbsp;= lg-specific, (2)&nbsp;analyzing&nbsp;functions&nbsp;= applicable&nbsp;across&nbsp;languages, hence lg-neutral.pp.85-106: categories from Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992 (-&gt; Trabasso et al 1989, Stein &amp; Glenn 1979) are used to model the stimulus story "Frog where are you", and for the coding schema for narrations of "Frog where are you" collected before B&amp;S 1994Berman &amp; Slobin_Coding schemaBackgroundPlot advancing elementsCircumstances or motivationsLater research converges how, relative to source?Later research diverges how, relative to source?Their narrative model has broad applicability largely through vague, undefined terms. This avoids the problem of having a precise model that only fits certain languages/cultures. But it's very limited in terms of studying differences in macrostructure.
To be fair, this is also because their main focus is microstructure, not macrostructure. Compare with ENNIBerman &amp; Slobin_NextRelevance todayAdults?Language acquisition
Cross-linguistic research; comparative linguisticsBerman &amp; Slobin_PurposeOnsetUnfoldingResolutionChildren?Other methods?Western, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?NB these sources have a variable level of engagement with Berman &amp; Slobin; what they have in common is the method.Works based on the same method, macrostructure:
Rungrojsuwan 2019 Thai / Monolingual research
Shunhua-Tianlong2023 Mandarin Chinese / Monolingual research Works based on the same method, microstructure
Klamer Moro 2020 Alorese, Teiwa (two languages of indonesia) / Monolingual research
Brown 2004 Tzeltal / Monolingual research
Bennett Kastor 2002 Irish + English bilinguals / Multilingual research, microstructure
Bavin 2000 WarlpiriTable of&nbsp;studies&nbsp;using&nbsp;Frog&nbsp;story on&nbsp;languages&nbsp;of&nbsp;Africa&nbsp;OverallConvergence relative to source:
Purpose: lang acq
Method: same method has been used abundantly before &amp; afterDivergence relative to source:
Purpose: lang descriptionBerman &amp; Slobin_Later researchWider range of purpose?Other cultures and languages, which?Speakers with mature lg skills?Monolingual speakers?Speakers with developing lg skills?Multilingual speakers?Different types of narratives?]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin__map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin__Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 11:33:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky__Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[Labov &amp; Waletzky in contextOperationalized model of Labov &amp; Waletzky 1967Evaluating whole models: does it suit...Later research based on Labov &amp; WaletzkyResearch participants demographicsNarrative modelOriginal source: Labov&nbsp;Waletzky&nbsp;1967Russian formalist narratology: Propp (p.13)Labov &amp; Waletzky_BackgroundInterviewer prompts a speaker to narrate a personal experience involving danger/risk of death
Data collected in two settings (with other community members, or without)
From a diverse set of speakers (variable age -- adults only --, race, and place of origin = +-urban).
Single language/cultureLabov &amp; Waletzky_MethodThis is a reconstruction; the description of the coding schema is scattered and incomplete.Transcription&nbsp;is&nbsp;divided&nbsp;into&nbsp;clauses.&nbsp;
All clauses are labelled.
A subset of verbs are labelled (+), which results in labelling all verbs (+/-).Labov &amp; Waletzky_Coding schemaSecondary sources:
doing-narrative-research2023_labov / Background,&nbsp;models&nbsp;and&nbsp;terms&nbsp;
berman1997_labov&nbsp;
johnstone2016_labov&nbsp;
Labov &amp;&nbsp;Waletzky&nbsp;(1967)&nbsp;developed&nbsp;a model to study narratives; specifically oral narrative by average speakers.
It is&nbsp;the&nbsp;most&nbsp;influential&nbsp;linguistic&nbsp;approach&nbsp;to date (perhaps&nbsp;with&nbsp;more influence in social sciences&nbsp;than&nbsp;linguistics&nbsp;per se). They&nbsp;innovated&nbsp;by&nbsp;studying&nbsp;oral versions of personal experiences narrated by average speakers, whereas&nbsp;previous&nbsp;research&nbsp;studied&nbsp;folk tales,&nbsp;myths,&nbsp;legends... narrated by expert storytellers. Labov &amp; Waletzky_Short description
Context: Prior research modeled narratives with a narrow, idealized dataset (myths, folk stories,... by expert storytellers). Better modeling can be achieved with a wider dataset (wider range of narratives, and of storytellers represented). (p.12) Implicit connection with lang acq (age variation) and variationist description (class, origin, race,... variation) This work models tellings of personal experiences by average speakers from diverse backgrounds. It enriches narrative research by considering new types of narratives, and a different set of storytellers. (p.12)
Purpose: Theory building
Labov &amp; Waletzky_PurposeLabov &amp; Waletzky_Terms
Limits of L&amp;W: Few macrostructure categories + fit poorly with other methods (&lt;-&gt; other types of narratives) + ?method not widely adopted? (ethical problem + not suitable for some populations)
Story grammar eg Stein &amp; Glenn improves on macrostructure granularity, accuracy, &amp; fit with multiple types of narrative &lt;-&gt; methods
Labov &amp; Waletzky_Next
Early example of work that analyzes how micro- &amp; macrostructure interface
Innovation in method to capture variationist data
Collecting data with more than one setting condition is valuable + has not been reproduced much
Labov &amp; Waletzky_Relevance todayAdults?Speakers with mature lg skills?Monolingual speakers?Multilingual speakers?Wider range of purpose?OrientationComplicationEvaluationResolutionCoda"Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Later research converges.md" ne peut pas être trouvé.Créer un nouveau fichierÉchanger le fichier...SupprimerNarrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Later research converges.mdPublications; purpose + participant demographicsSome&nbsp;engagement&nbsp;with&nbsp;Labov in&nbsp;these&nbsp;articles:&nbsp;
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Nicolas%20%20Ntuli%202025&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Bb391e7be-c9d1-403f-974a-6c3694a1d1e8%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Nicolas&nbsp; Ntuli 2025</a>&nbsp;-- uses L&amp;W&nbsp;categories&nbsp;for&nbsp;its&nbsp;coding&nbsp;
Rungrojsuwan&nbsp;2019&nbsp;&nbsp;
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Shunhua-Tianlong2023&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Bbdf8ec2e-b2c1-4675-ac25-aad358e6e016%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Shunhua-Tianlong2023</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;
Todo&nbsp;find&nbsp;more&nbsp;research&nbsp;of&nbsp;this&nbsp;type&nbsp;Converges how, relative to source?(TBC)
Terms, definitions, coding schemas (partial)
Purpose (lang acq, variationist description)Diverges how, relative to source?(TBC)
Method
Terms, definitions and coding schemas (partial)
Purpose (? discourse studies ?)Labov &amp; Waletzky_Later research"Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Later research diverges.md" ne peut pas être trouvé.Créer un nouveau fichierÉchanger le fichier...SupprimerNarrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Later research diverges.mdChildren?Macrostructure categories fit poorly other methods (eg storyboard elicitation).Other methods?Speakers with developing lg skills?Other cultures and languages, which?Different types of narratives?Poor fit, BUT! They capture concepts that get largely ignored by later research (evaluation &amp; coda ≈ metanarration)Western, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky__map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky__Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 11:33:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Notes meeting 24.11]]></title><description><![CDATA[Tasks
Track time when adding references to docx
Aim for 1 Article/week
Memo
CC Masha in communication with VV
Can ask for help if there are communication problems (cultural diff) with VV
Tasks todo this week are in bold; they mostly connect to identification of EpisodesRe adapting narrative units to African context: Look into Tatiana Nikitina's work on storytelling (talk in Kirikou folder; Tatiana episode 4)
look into her source on Ancient Greek
look into Labov 1972
(? Look into research discourse particle &amp; narration)
Incorporate narratology/folklore/lit studies = OK
See Masha's email (Copy of Frog's email)
Transformative variations in the telling and transmission of tales have been a center of interest and discussion since the nineteenth century. Early research viewed stories as having ideal forms that suffer from corruptions and contaminations (e.g. Krohn 1926 [1971]: chs. 9–11). However, variation has become viewed as organic to oral storytelling, with more nuanced approaches to diverse types of observable variation (e.g. Honko 1981), how variation relates to a teller's attitudes, inclinations, and interpretations (e.g. Siikala 1990), and the development of tools for more sophisticated analysis (Frog 2021).Berman &amp; Slobin:
check episode, check event
(does not seem helpful for micro-macro study)
MAIN:
check later research to see how function/form gets annotated, analyzed; see paper on Afrikaans, Xhosa
how do they annotate into episodes?
Trabasso &amp; Nickels:
how do they annotate into episodes?
Look into Pear stories, Chafe~ MK will write to Helpdesk to install Obsidian
OTOH backup plan: Find a way to host notes onlineRead about adapting narrative structure to African contextDecide on narrative model -&gt; Decide on function coding schema
(Challenges: circularity between concepts
under-defined terms
not enough transparency in coding &amp; analysis -&gt; where's the start/end of an episode?)
Sequence -&gt; Connectivity = clause-linking marker LE, YELE,... DONC, BE
Copy annotated data &amp; highlight clause-linking markers,= + tail-head (in REP &amp; tail head column)
Create new column 'Connectivity' that aggregates highlights from step 1
? Create column correspondence-w-source-material
? Create column macrostructure-of-the-narration
? Annotate metanarrative units
(Memo: tidy data principle; lumping multiple columns is trivial, so more columns than needed = better than fewer than needed)Masha gives me conceptual lead = responsibility for technical implementation, annotation, writing (accuracy of claims)
George Moroz (GM) will take care of stats
Analysis = making sense of stats, shared with MashaI can ask for guidance (however much I need)
HSSH Catalyst grant application CC'd outlines some of the responsibilities (annotation, consolidation into database)]]></description><link>narrative-models/6_collab-forth./notes-meeting-24.11.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/6_Collab forth./Notes meeting 24.11.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 11:24:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Coding schema]]></title><description><![CDATA[Transcription is divided into "communication units, each of which consisted either of (1) one independent clause plus any dependent clauses associated with it, or (2) of a sentence fragment".Tellings are given a score, rather than coded, same as MAIN (?? is there a purpose-dependent splie like MAIN actually??).
The scoring procedure is described (p. 230-231) + examples shown in Appendix (final page).]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN__Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[MAIN in contextOperationalized model of MAINNarrative model (2019)NarrativeEpisodeEvaluating whole models: does it suit...Later research based on MAINCore componentsResearch participants demographicsGoal or alternativeInternal statesCompare with ENNIMAIN_BackgroundDiagnostic evaluation
Language acquisition, cross-linguistic comparisonIts main purpose is to screen for language impairments among bilingual children, and monolingual children, with the same protocol.MAIN_PurposeStoryboard elicitation. Set of four stories presented through a sequence of 6 pictures. These stories were designed directly for MAIN. They are controlled for complexity, and cross-cultural appropriateness.Data collected from children &amp; adults (adults serve as benchmarks for children)
Multiple languages/cultures; monolingual and multilingualMAIN_MethodTranscription rules are very explicit &amp; precise (see <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Transcription_rules.pdf" data-href="Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Transcription_rules.pdf" href="narrative-models/5_main/main_transcription_rules.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">MAIN_Transcription_rules</a>), probably informed by conversation analysis.
Annotation procedure much less so.
Description of annotation is given in: <br>Gagarina et al 2012_MAIN <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="gagarina-et-al2012_MAIN.pdf > page=19" data-href="gagarina-et-al2012_MAIN.pdf#page=19" href="narrative-models/5_main/gagarina-et-al2012_main.html#page=19" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">p.13</a>: Westby's decision tree shown as guide to code episodes. Gagarina et al 2019_MAIN_Adult p.197-198: This article lists the categories, without describing the process. Multiple coders with high agreement.
Lindgren Bohnacker 2022 p.492: This article lists the coding categories, without describing the process.
Klopp &amp; Smith 2025 p.181-182: Coding of macrostructure relies on Westby's decision tree. Data labelled as "no sequence" receive an additional label: description, or action. Two coders, with high agreement. No description of process beyond that.<br>
Started looking for an annotated dataset on MAIN's website. Could continue: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://zenodo.org/records/4724970#.Yf1qqKbMK5d" target="_self">https://zenodo.org/records/4724970#.Yf1qqKbMK5d</a>
They have a standard annotation procedure that produces high agreement between codes. It's practical for their purpose, but flawed theory-wise. Checked other sources to see if I could find a more recent &amp; comprehensive annotation procedure; I did not find anything of the sort.
Gagarina &amp; Bohnacker 2019_MAIN-revised
Lindgren et al 2019
<br>Full package of MAIN documents on website; Transcription Rules does not touch on annotation. See <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844" target="_self">https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844</a>
Old notesExamples of score rubric shown in Gagarina et al 2012: 67-86
One score rubric created per story
The score rubric has more or less items depending on the complexity &amp; length of the story.Here's a rough adaptation:The rubric also tracks:
Quantified version of "Structural complexity" Nb of AO sequences
Nb of G (no AO) sequences
Nb of GA / GO sequence
Nb of GAO sequences Nb of internal state terms (total and nb by type)
When adapting this protocol for labelling data, quantification of structural complexity can flow directly from coding data with macrostructure categories.
MAIN_Coding schemaShort description
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Gagarina%20et%20al%202012&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Bf4ca0616-b4ae-4966-8408-979919791ea3%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Gagarina et al 2012</a>&nbsp;_ MAIN (presentation&nbsp;of the&nbsp;method&nbsp;&amp; design&nbsp;behind&nbsp;it = unrevised version) / Background,&nbsp;models&nbsp;and&nbsp;terms, source&nbsp;mining
Gagarina &amp; Bohnacker 2019 introduces the revised model; Revised materials &amp; transcription procedure are online <br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844" target="_self">https://www.leibniz-zas.de/de/publications/schriftenreihe/zaspil/zaspil-63/main-63-download#c2844</a> Benchmark:
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="onenote:Reading%20notes.one#Gagarina%20et%20al%202019&amp;section-id=%7Bc4881620-dd63-4b4f-b168-556f6442eedd%7D&amp;page-id=%7Ba9fc09b6-5323-4c7c-beea-493aced102ff%7D&amp;end" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href=".html" target="_self">Gagarina et al 2019</a>&nbsp;- German,&nbsp;Russian,&nbsp;Swedish;&nbsp;adults&nbsp;/&nbsp;Monolingual&nbsp;research, background, cultural variation,&nbsp;theory&nbsp;
Metastudy:
Lindgren et al 2019 _ MAIN (review&nbsp;of&nbsp;studies&nbsp;on&nbsp;multilingual&nbsp;children) /&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research
MAIN_Original sourcesPartial list:
Lindgren &amp;&nbsp;Bohnacker&nbsp;2022 _ German,&nbsp;Swedish&nbsp;/&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Tribushinina,&nbsp;Irmawati&nbsp;&amp; Mak 2022 _&nbsp;Indonesian, Dutch /&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Bohnacker, Lindgren &amp;&nbsp;Öztekin&nbsp;2022 _ Turkish,&nbsp;Swedish&nbsp;/&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Fiani, Henry &amp; Prévost 2022 _&nbsp;Lebanese&nbsp;Arabic, French /&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;&nbsp;
Fichman&nbsp;&amp; al 2022 _&nbsp;Russian,&nbsp;Hebrew&nbsp;/&nbsp;Multilingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Kosutar&nbsp;et al 2022 _&nbsp;Croatian&nbsp;/&nbsp;Monolingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Lindgren 2019 _&nbsp;Swedish&nbsp;/&nbsp;Monolingual&nbsp;research&nbsp;
Klop&nbsp;&amp; Smith 2025 _ Afrikaans, Xhosa
See also: <br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/publications/" target="_self">https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/publications/</a>
<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/projects/" target="_self">https://main.leibniz-zas.de/en/research/projects/</a>
MAIN_Later researchLater research converges how, relative to source?Later research diverges how, relative to source?SettingTerms and def. taken from Gagarina et al 2019 (revised model)
I may find more later, there's scattering in between initial &amp; revised model (3 publications or more)MAIN_Terms(Secondary sources)Adults?Children?Other methods?Speakers with mature lg skills?Speakers with developing lg skills?Wider range of purpose?Monolingual speakers?Other episodesInitiating eventWestern, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?Other cultures and languages, which?Multilingual speakers?Initial internal stateReactionGoalAttemptInitial internal state as initiating eventOutcomeCompare with our model ... ??Relevance todayDifferent types of narratives?]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main__map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN__Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 18:05:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Map]]></title><description><![CDATA[Whole model in contextEvaluating whole models: does it suit...Operationalized model of Authors YYYYResearch participants demographicsLater research based on Authors YYYYNarrative modelPurpose: research topic, practical useBackground: How does it build on, &amp; connect to earlier models?Original source(Secondary sources)Short descriptionAdults?Children?Terms &amp; DefinitionsMethodCoding schemaSpeakers with mature lg skills?Western, or Rich/Industrialized cultures (&amp; their dominant languages)?Monolingual speakers?Multilingual speakers?Speakers with developing lg skills?Sequel
Limitations connect to Background of subsequent modelRelevance todayWider range of purpose?Other cultures and languages, which?Other methods?Later research converges how, relative to source?Later research diverges how, relative to source?Publications; purpose + participant demographicsDifferent types of narratives?]]></description><link>narrative-models/0_meta/map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/Map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 18:05:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[lang 2003 1]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/lang-2003-1.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/lang 2003 1.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:19:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[lindgren2019_swedish]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/lindgren2019_swedish.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/lindgren2019_swedish.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[lindgren-et-al2019_MAIN]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/lindgren-et-al2019_main.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/lindgren-et-al2019_MAIN.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lee2013]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/lee2013.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Lee2013.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[lang 2003]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/lang-2003.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/lang 2003.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[kosutar-et-al2022_croatian]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/kosutar-et-al2022_croatian.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/kosutar-et-al2022_croatian.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[klamer moro 2020 _ alorese teiwa]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/klamer-moro-2020-_-alorese-teiwa.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/klamer moro 2020 _ alorese teiwa.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[johnstone2016_labov]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/johnstone2016_labov.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/johnstone2016_labov.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gutierrez-Clellen Quinn 1993]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/gutierrez-clellen-quinn-1993.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Gutierrez-Clellen Quinn 1993.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[gimenez2010]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/gimenez2010.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/gimenez2010.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[fichman-et-al2022_russian_hebrew]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/fichman-et-al2022_russian_hebrew.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/fichman-et-al2022_russian_hebrew.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[fiani-henry-prévost2022_lebanese_french]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/fiani-henry-prévost2022_lebanese_french.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/fiani-henry-prévost2022_lebanese_french.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dombrowsky-Hahn 2012]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/dombrowsky-hahn-2012.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Dombrowsky-Hahn 2012.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[doing-narrative-research2013_labov]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/doing-narrative-research2013_labov.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/doing-narrative-research2013_labov.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[doing-narrative-research2013_intro]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/doing-narrative-research2013_intro.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/doing-narrative-research2013_intro.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[brown_2004_tzeltal]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/brown_2004_tzeltal.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/brown_2004_tzeltal.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[bohnacker-lindgren-öztekin2022_turkish_swedish]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/bohnacker-lindgren-öztekin2022_turkish_swedish.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/bohnacker-lindgren-öztekin2022_turkish_swedish.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[berman1997_labov]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/berman1997_labov.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/berman1997_labov.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[bennett-kastor2002_irish eng bilinguals]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/bennett-kastor2002_irish-eng-bilinguals.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/bennett-kastor2002_irish eng bilinguals.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[bavin2000_warlpiri]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/bavin2000_warlpiri.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/bavin2000_warlpiri.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Agyeman2016]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/agyeman2016.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Agyeman2016.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[abdalla-mahfoudhi-alhudhainah2020_arabic]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/abdalla-mahfoudhi-alhudhainah2020_arabic.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/abdalla-mahfoudhi-alhudhainah2020_arabic.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[westby et al 2002]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/westby-et-al-2002.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/westby et al 2002.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[trubishinina-irmawati-mak2022_indonesian_dutch]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/trubishinina-irmawati-mak2022_indonesian_dutch.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/trubishinina-irmawati-mak2022_indonesian_dutch.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tappe2018]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/tappe2018.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Tappe2018.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[tappe-hara2013]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/tappe-hara2013.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/tappe-hara2013.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[soodla-kikas2010_estonian]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/soodla-kikas2010_estonian.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/soodla-kikas2010_estonian.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[shunhua-tianlong2023_Chinese]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/shunhua-tianlong2023_chinese.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/shunhua-tianlong2023_Chinese.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[rungrojsuwan2019_thai]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/rungrojsuwan2019_thai.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/rungrojsuwan2019_thai.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rungrojsuwan 2023_Thai]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/rungrojsuwan-2023_thai.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Rungrojsuwan 2023_Thai.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Roth 2019]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/roth-2019.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Roth 2019.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[romaine2009_first_nations]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/romaine2009_first_nations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/romaine2009_first_nations.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[perez-et-al-2023_spanish_english]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/perez-et-al-2023_spanish_english.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/perez-et-al-2023_spanish_english.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[nomagugu2020_english_Siswati]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/nomagugu2020_english_siswati.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/nomagugu2020_english_Siswati.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[nicolas-ntuli-english_sesotho_sepitori_etc]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/nicolas-ntuli-english_sesotho_sepitori_etc.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/nicolas-ntuli-english_sesotho_sepitori_etc.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mous 2022]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/mous-2022.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Mous 2022.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mous 2004]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/mous-2004.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Mous 2004.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Markgraf 2015]]></title><link>article-notes/sources/markgraf-2015.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Sources/Markgraf 2015.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:14:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare w Labov &amp; Waletzky
Situate in story grammar models from the 70s]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 16:51:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shunhua-Tianlong2023]]></title><description><![CDATA[Engagement with Labov and Story Grammar models incl. Stein &amp; Glenn 1979 Purpose: "With the intention of understanding age-related disparities, the study aimed to explore narrative macrostructure and specific measures of story grammar ability scores, such as story background, story cause, attempt, story results, and internal response. Additionally, it sought to investigate how the development of narrative macrostructure in Chinese preschoolers relates to their cause-and-effect logical reasoning abilities." (p.2457) Utterances were coded with a set of categories based on Story Grammar model
p.2459:
<img alt="shunhua-tianlong2023_2459.png" src="article-notes/images/shunhua-tianlong2023_2459.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/shunhua-tianlong2023.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Shunhua-Tianlong2023.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Short description]]></title><description><![CDATA[Multilingual Assesment Instrument for Narratives (MAIN) is a set of methods and tools designed to study children's (age 3-10) narrative skills in one or more languages.
MAIN seems like the most popular framework for narrative research involving macrostructure in recent years. There's a large body of research available: monolingual, multilingual, adult benchmarks,... The range of languages/cultures covered is significant but still heavily skews towards Europe. There's also been a real effort to make the macrostructure model relevant to a large range of languages/cultures. Study with MAIN conducted in Africa seems limited to Afrikaans-English + Afrikaans-Xhosa (South Africa). ]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_short-description.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Short description.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MAIN_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare with ENNI]]></description><link>narrative-models/5_main/main_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/MAIN_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare with Berman &amp; Slobin]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Next]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compare with Berman &amp; Slobin]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_next.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Next.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Method]]></title><description><![CDATA[Storyboard elicitation (Frog, Where Are You?)
Data collected from children. ? ADULTS (probably included too?
Multiple language/cultures (English, Spanish, German, Hebrew, Turkish); monolingualThere are many studies based on eliciting retellings of the Frog story (1979). Some of them analyze narrative macrostructure.
Most studies focus on microstructure, not macrostructure.
Findings from this type of study are limited, because it's a single story and not designed to control for complexity or cultural appropriateness like MAIN.
Frog story studies are often done on minority languages, and they represent a highly diverse set of languages/cultures. ]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Short description]]></title><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_short-description.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Short description.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 14:37:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ENNI_Short description]]></title><description><![CDATA[Standard procedure of method + scoring for diagnostic evaluation, and lang acquisition research
Just based on English participants, no discussion of cross-cultural or cross-linguistic applicability ]]></description><link>narrative-models/4_enni/enni_short-description.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/ENNI_Short description.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Terms]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internal system:
First&nbsp;element&nbsp;(enabler) = (1)
Second&nbsp;element&nbsp;and/or top&nbsp;category = (2)&nbsp;
Some&nbsp;elements&nbsp;can&nbsp;appear&nbsp;out of the&nbsp;sequence&nbsp;they&nbsp;present&nbsp;(p.67).&nbsp;
]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tappe & Hara 2013]]></title><description><![CDATA[Chichewa-English The coding schema is described indirectly (p.317) Categories are: Repetitions Opening formulae Closing formulae Dialogues Setting (canonical element in Story Grammar) Internal Response (canonical element in Story Grammar) The categories are mostly based on what the authors identify as elements of African narratives. Some are based on Story Grammar, specifically elements thought to be canonical. p.299 Authors argue that language- and culture-specific differences are not always reconcilable with the Story Grammar model developed by Steinn &amp; Glenn, and Anderson &amp; Evans "existing research does not concentrate on macro-structural differences between texts produced in different languages, while a huge number of language families are under-represented in or absent from such research" The literature is now more diverse in terms of language studied than at time of publication, but huge gaps still exist. p.299-300 ]]></description><link>article-notes/tappe-&amp;-hara-2013.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Tappe &amp; Hara 2013.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[shunhua-tianlong2023_2459]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/shunhua-tianlong2023_2459.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/shunhua-tianlong2023_2459.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/shunhua-tianlong2023_2459.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:59:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nicolas & Ntuli 2025]]></title><description><![CDATA[English, Sepitori, Sesotho etc.
Multilingual participantsp.6-7
"The story is categorised into a macrostructure schema of the cartoon (Colletta et al., 2015)." (list of macro-episodes after that)
"We utilised a multi-tier coding grid in ELAN1 to facilitate transcription and annotation, initially developed for the Colletta et al. (2015) cross-linguistic study and an accompanying coding manual. This manual outlines adapted transcription rules from the Belgium VALI- BEL system (Dister et al., 2009), defines the linguistic and gestural variables for analysis, explains the tier-by-tier coding process, and offers examples for each variable. This anno- tation scheme offers valuable insights into various aspects of language, including lexical (words), syntax, and discourse analysis. (Colletta et al., 2015; Kunene Nicolas et al., 2017). "
A bit confusing. I think they transcribed the telling based on a schema from Colletta et al 2015. But that paper does not talk about macrostructure (checked multiple times that it's the right publication)! So I don't see how they could have coded macrostructure based on it. Identification of macro-episodes is not really explained. p.7 Classification of each clause to one or more discourse function (based on Labov &amp; Waletzky and Neil 1992): Narrating Explaining Interpreting Commenting p.7 Clauses that didn't fit any of these categories were labelled Interactive clause (eg rhetorical question, direct address to audience) p.8 Some words were coded to "measure lexical referents used". Important referents in the story were each given a code; then this code was used for each turn of phrase sharing the referrent, as in this example from p.11: <img alt="nicolas_ntuli_2025_11.png" src="article-notes/images/nicolas_ntuli_2025_11.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/nicolas-&amp;-ntuli-2025.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Nicolas &amp; Ntuli 2025.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:50 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Abdalla, Mahfoudhi & Alhudhainah 2020]]></title><description><![CDATA[Method:&nbsp;Used&nbsp;ENNI = a set of&nbsp;picture&nbsp;stories&nbsp;based&nbsp;on Stein &amp;&nbsp;Glenn's&nbsp;1979 (?).
This set was chosen because it was already used to study Canadien children in English &amp; French, hence&nbsp;it&nbsp;would&nbsp;permit&nbsp;some&nbsp;cross-linguistic&nbsp;and cross-cultural&nbsp;comparison.&nbsp;Kuwaiti Arabicp.4&nbsp;describes&nbsp;the&nbsp;coding. It&nbsp;was&nbsp;done&nbsp;using&nbsp;the ENNI&nbsp;scoring&nbsp;criteria&nbsp;with&nbsp;slight&nbsp;modifications.&nbsp;Each&nbsp;telling&nbsp;gets&nbsp;a single score&nbsp;based&nbsp;on&nbsp;its&nbsp;degree&nbsp;of&nbsp;completeness&nbsp;Findings:&nbsp;&nbsp;
p.6-7: Story&nbsp;complexity&nbsp;increased&nbsp;with&nbsp;age&nbsp;but&nbsp;didn't&nbsp;meet&nbsp;the&nbsp;adult&nbsp;benchmark.&nbsp;Results&nbsp;with&nbsp;Kuwaiti&nbsp;children&nbsp;are comparable to&nbsp;results&nbsp;of&nbsp;study&nbsp;done&nbsp;with&nbsp;Canadian&nbsp;children,&nbsp;suggesting&nbsp;ENNI&nbsp;is&nbsp;suitable&nbsp;for adaptation&nbsp;across&nbsp;languages&nbsp;and cultures.&nbsp;&nbsp;
p.7:&nbsp;Children&nbsp;had&nbsp;similar&nbsp;scores&nbsp;when&nbsp;telling&nbsp;simple and&nbsp;complex&nbsp;stories&nbsp;alike,&nbsp;whereas&nbsp;adults' score&nbsp;showed&nbsp;a&nbsp;difference&nbsp;(better&nbsp;performance on simple stories).&nbsp;&nbsp;
p.8:&nbsp;Children&nbsp;and&nbsp;adults&nbsp;were&nbsp;more&nbsp;likely&nbsp;to&nbsp;include&nbsp;core&nbsp;elements&nbsp;than&nbsp;complementary&nbsp;ones,&nbsp;which&nbsp;is&nbsp;in line&nbsp;with&nbsp;previous&nbsp;research&nbsp;in&nbsp;other&nbsp;languages.&nbsp;&nbsp;
p.9: No&nbsp;effect&nbsp;of story&nbsp;complexity&nbsp;found.&nbsp;Core&nbsp;macrostructure&nbsp;elements&nbsp;were&nbsp;mastered&nbsp;before&nbsp;complementary&nbsp;ones.&nbsp;&nbsp;
p.2-3.&nbsp;Arabic&nbsp;is&nbsp;highly&nbsp;diglossic.&nbsp;Imo,&nbsp;authors&nbsp;tell&nbsp;little&nbsp;about the&nbsp;consequences&nbsp;on&nbsp;expected&nbsp;results&nbsp;or&nbsp;study&nbsp;design.&nbsp;They&nbsp;point out&nbsp;that&nbsp;each&nbsp;Arabic&nbsp;dialect&nbsp;requires&nbsp;different&nbsp;assessment&nbsp;tools, and on p.8,&nbsp;that&nbsp;research&nbsp;needs&nbsp;to focus on&nbsp;spoken&nbsp;dialects&nbsp;&amp; storytelling practices at home.&nbsp; Story&nbsp;Grammar&nbsp;model&nbsp;
p. 5-6: the model&nbsp;used&nbsp;involve&nbsp;Core&nbsp;VS&nbsp;complementary&nbsp;story&nbsp;grammar.&nbsp;&nbsp; Core&nbsp;=&nbsp;initiating&nbsp;event&nbsp;+&nbsp;attempt&nbsp;(main&nbsp;character's&nbsp;response&nbsp;to the&nbsp;initiating&nbsp;event) +&nbsp;outcome&nbsp;(consequences&nbsp;of the&nbsp;attempt).&nbsp;&nbsp;
Complementary&nbsp;= setting +&nbsp;characters&nbsp;+&nbsp;reactions&nbsp;(characters' feelings or&nbsp;thoughts&nbsp;about&nbsp;outcomes). All&nbsp;age&nbsp;groups&nbsp;were&nbsp;more&nbsp;likely&nbsp;to&nbsp;include&nbsp;core&nbsp;elements&nbsp;than&nbsp;complementary&nbsp;elements.&nbsp; p.9: The&nbsp;tendency&nbsp;to&nbsp;exclude&nbsp;internal&nbsp;states (among&nbsp;children&nbsp;and&nbsp;adults)&nbsp;might&nbsp;be&nbsp;a cultural&nbsp;difference.&nbsp;&nbsp;
p.10: 'Internal&nbsp;plan', 'internal&nbsp;response' and 'reaction' do not&nbsp;seem&nbsp;like essential&nbsp;elements&nbsp;of stories of&nbsp;adults,&nbsp;because&nbsp;they&nbsp;often&nbsp;excluded&nbsp;them,&nbsp;whereas&nbsp;they&nbsp;always&nbsp;included&nbsp;'setting' and 'characters'. This&nbsp;finding&nbsp;is&nbsp;specific&nbsp;to&nbsp;this&nbsp;study, and not&nbsp;reflected&nbsp;in the&nbsp;study&nbsp;on Canadian&nbsp;children.&nbsp;So the notion of&nbsp;core&nbsp;and&nbsp;complementary&nbsp;elements&nbsp;needs&nbsp;revision&nbsp;(to&nbsp;account&nbsp;for cultural&nbsp;differences).
]]></description><link>article-notes/abdalla,-mahfoudhi-&amp;-alhudhainah-2020.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Abdalla, Mahfoudhi &amp; Alhudhainah 2020.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Romaine 2009]]></title><description><![CDATA[Study with First Nation research participantsTranscripts were not annotated, rather given a score. The score method is the McKeough Oral Narrative Evaluation Rubric, p.20:
<img alt="romaine2009_20.png" src="article-notes/images/romaine2009_20.png" target="_self">p.13-14: First Nation narratives "typically jump into the story without providing background information". FN narrative structures "often uses thematic sequencing where one idea is followed by several other ideas" (as opposed to chronological sequencing), and connections between ideas are left implicit. So Western audiences view these stories as lacking cohesion. The resolution of FN narratives tend to be about impact to the community, rather than the individual. p.43: "Culture. Lastly, in their study of cross-cultural differences, Ball (2008), Gutierrez-Clellen and Quinn (1993), and Westby, Moore and Roman (2002) have noted that culture influences a variety of factors related to the development of narrative capacity. ]]></description><link>article-notes/romaine-2009.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Romaine 2009.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:56:47 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rungrojsuwan 2019]]></title><description><![CDATA[ThaiCompare Rungrojsuwan 2023 Language acquisition study Some engagement with Labov Not given in text. p.6: The tiers of the transcripts are phonetic transcription, word-by-word gloss, translation of whole utterance in English. Macrostructure elements were evaluated based on sentence meaning, and aggregated in quantitative data, so there has to be some annotation of the type we're after. I could email the author? ]]></description><link>article-notes/rungrojsuwan-2019.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Rungrojsuwan 2019.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:56:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[romaine2009_20]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/romaine2009_20.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/romaine2009_20.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/romaine2009_20.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:52:59 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gagarina et al 2012]]></title><description><![CDATA[Purpose of the model p.2 "Our intent was to develop materials for the assessment of narratives in both languages of bilingual children in order to screen and identify children at risk for Specific Language Impairment (SLI)." Bilingual pairs studied for this publication (listed on p.94- 97): Afrikaans, English Dutch, Turkish English, Hebrew English, Polish Finnish, Russian Finnish, Swedish German, Russian German, Turkish Greek, Albanian Italian, English Lithuanian, Russian Swedish, English Swedish, French Swedish, Russian Greek, Albanian Greek, Albanian, Bulgarian, French, German, Romanian. (exact pairing is unclear in the source page) = bilinguals with SLI Swedish, Russian = bilinguals with SLI Mostly Indo-European and/or spoken in Europe. 4 language families in total, and 2 sites of research outside Europe: Israel, South Africa. p.20:
<img alt="gagarina_et_al2012_20.png" src="article-notes/images/gagarina_et_al2012_20.png" target="_self">Transcripts are scored, not annotated. They created a score grid with sections for each macrostructure element of their model. Examples of transcript and scoring are presented in pp.67-86.<br>
<img alt="gagarina_et_al_67...86.png" src="article-notes/images/gagarina_et_al_67...86.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/gagarina-et-al-2012.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Gagarina et al 2012.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:52 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[gagarina_et_al_67...86]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/gagarina_et_al_67...86.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/gagarina_et_al_67...86.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/gagarina_et_al_67...86.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:51:35 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[gagarina_et_al2012_20]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/gagarina_et_al2012_20.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/gagarina_et_al2012_20.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/gagarina_et_al2012_20.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:50:25 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gagarina et al 2019]]></title><description><![CDATA[This study had monolingual adults as participants; speakers of German, Swedish, and Russian. It sets a benchmark for studies with children. p.192-193:
Models of narrative complexity developed in the 70s-80s. Narrative = setting + one or more episodes. Episode = initiating event + internal response + internal plan + attempt + direct consequence + reaction. An episode might not have all of these elements; episodes are more or less complex depending on the number of elements present. Stein &amp; Glenn's 1979 story grammar model is one of those models. It is still used in recent narrative research. p. 193:
MAIN builds on these prior models. The model developed involves complete unites (episodes) that have 5 components. 2 of them (initiation, and reaction; internal states of the protagonist) frame the 3 components that form the core content of the episode: Goal, Attempt, Outcome. The narrative also needs a statement setting (time &amp; place) at the start. Research with MAIN can be qualitative or quantitative (p.193-194), and involves telling stories based on a set of images. The set was designed for broad cross-cultural appropriateness. p.204: Participants had similar production regardless of language groups. -&gt; "This is good evidence for the pictorial stimuli being cross-linguistically and cross-culturally robust, at least for three groups of monolingual adults (all Europeans, and all literate)" Imo it doesn't demonstrate appropriateness beyond Western cultures and languages. But then again, a lot of narrative research seems developed for use in evaluating students, educational needs &amp; language impairment; this creates a bias towards tools that are "cross-cultural" but only really need to be relevant for WEIRD populations, by which I mean industrialized/rich moreso than Western. p.204-205: "story complexity was not found to differ significantly, neither between languages nor between stories (Baby Goats vs. Baby Birds). This finding suggests that story complexity (i.e. the qualitative evaluation of macrostructure) may be of a more universal nature than story structure." Complexity here was a matter of number of episodes with full Goal-Action-Outcome sequences. p.205-206:
Goals are not always explicitly included in narratives of adult -- this creates a problem for the theory, because goals are seen as central to narratives, and their omission can't be attributed to the storytellers' low skills.
The authors resolve this by formulating alternatives to GAO. 1) IAO sequence (internal state as initiating event, attempt, outcome). 'Internal states' were included more frequently than Goals, and they can be the starting point of an episode. 2) EAO sequence (initiating event, attempt, outcome) ]]></description><link>article-notes/gagarina-et-al-2019.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Gagarina et al 2019.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[nicolas_ntuli_2025_11]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="article-notes/images/nicolas_ntuli_2025_11.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>article-notes/images/nicolas_ntuli_2025_11.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Article notes/Images/nicolas_ntuli_2025_11.png</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:46:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Terms]]></title><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Short description]]></title><description><![CDATA[Labov &amp;&nbsp;Waletzky&nbsp;(1967)&nbsp;developed&nbsp;a model to study narratives; specifically oral narrative by average speakers.
It is&nbsp;the&nbsp;most&nbsp;influential&nbsp;linguistic&nbsp;approach&nbsp;to date (perhaps&nbsp;with&nbsp;more influence in social sciences&nbsp;than&nbsp;linguistics&nbsp;per se). They&nbsp;innovated&nbsp;by&nbsp;studying&nbsp;oral versions of personal experiences narrated by average speakers, whereas&nbsp;previous&nbsp;research&nbsp;studied&nbsp;folk tales,&nbsp;myths,&nbsp;legends... narrated by expert storytellers. ]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_short-description.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Short description.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Next]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Limits of L&amp;W: Few macrostructure categories + fit poorly with other methods (&lt;-&gt; other types of narratives) + ?method not widely adopted? (ethical problem + not suitable for some populations)
Story grammar eg Stein &amp; Glenn improves on macrostructure granularity, accuracy, &amp; fit with multiple types of narrative &lt;-&gt; methods
]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_next.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Next.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Context: Prior research modeled narratives with a narrow, idealized dataset (myths, folk stories,... by expert storytellers). Better modeling can be achieved with a wider dataset (wider range of narratives, and of storytellers represented). (p.12) Implicit connection with lang acq (age variation) and variationist description (class, origin, race,... variation) This work models tellings of personal experiences by average speakers from diverse backgrounds. It enriches narrative research by considering new types of narratives, and a different set of storytellers. (p.12)
Purpose: Theory building
]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Method]]></title><description><![CDATA[Interviewer prompts a speaker to narrate a personal experience involving danger/risk of death
Data collected in two settings (with other community members, or without)
From a diverse set of speakers (variable age -- adults only --, race, and place of origin = +-urban).
Single language/culture]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Coding schema]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is a reconstruction; the description of the coding schema is scattered and incomplete.Transcription&nbsp;is&nbsp;divided&nbsp;into&nbsp;clauses.&nbsp;
All clauses are labelled.
A subset of verbs are labelled (+), which results in labelling all verbs (+/-).]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[Russian formalist narratology: Propp (p.13)]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berman & Slobin_Next]]></title><description><![CDATA[Their narrative model has broad applicability largely through vague, undefined terms. This avoids the problem of having a precise model that only fits certain languages/cultures. But it's very limited in terms of studying differences in macrostructure.
To be fair, this is also because their main focus is microstructure, not macrostructure. Compare with ENNI]]></description><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/berman-&amp;-slobin_next.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Berman &amp; Slobin_Next.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Labov & Waletzky_Relevance today]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Early example of work that analyzes how micro- &amp; macrostructure interface
Innovation in method to capture variationist data
Collecting data with more than one setting condition is valuable + has not been reproduced much
]]></description><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/labov-&amp;-waletzky_relevance-today.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Labov &amp; Waletzky_Relevance today.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Method]]></title><description><![CDATA[Storyboard elicitation (Frog, Where Are You?)
Data collected from children and adults
Single language/culture (American English)]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Short description]]></title><description><![CDATA[Stein &amp;&nbsp;Glenn's&nbsp;model&nbsp;is&nbsp;the story&nbsp;grammar&nbsp;model&nbsp;from&nbsp;the 70-80s&nbsp;that&nbsp;gets&nbsp;cited&nbsp;the&nbsp;most. It's extremely granular. It focuses on modeling underlying stories, rather than narrations of stories. (It's the same distinction as deep syntax with nesting, empty categories,... vs surface-only.)This confused me for a bit: the actual model used when citing Stein &amp; Glenn is not theirs; it's a synthesis, most similar to Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992.]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_short-description.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Short description.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trabasso & Nickels_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[Berman 1988
Trabasso &amp; al 1989 (discourse analysis)Compare with Stein &amp; Glenn]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/trabasso-&amp;-nickels_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Trabasso &amp; Nickels_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:28:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Terms]]></title><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_terms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Terms.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 10:27:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[TrabassoNickels1992]]></title><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/2_trabasso-&amp;-nickels-1992/primary-source/trabassonickels1992.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/2_Trabasso &amp; Nickels 1992/Primary source/TrabassoNickels1992.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 09:39:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[LabovWaletzky1967]]></title><link>narrative-models/1_labov-&amp;-waletzky/primary-source/labovwaletzky1967.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/1_Labov &amp; Waletzky/Primary source/LabovWaletzky1967.pdf</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:32:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Which research topic and/or practical use?]]></description><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_purpose.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Purpose.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 20:52:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[How does it build on, &amp; connect to earlier models?]]></description><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Background.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 20:52:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Method]]></title><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_method.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Method.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 15:40:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Later research diverges]]></title><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_later-research-diverges.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Later research diverges.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 15:40:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Later research converges]]></title><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_later-research-converges.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Later research converges.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 15:39:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Later research]]></title><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_later-research.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Later research.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 15:39:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Coding schema]]></title><link>narrative-models/0_meta/x_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/0_Meta/X_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 15:39:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stein & Glenn_Coding schema]]></title><description><![CDATA[Incomplete description (it's a single paragraph on p.88).
Data is given a score; no full transcription, no systematic data labelling.Roughly corresponds to:An excellent idea they had was to create story schemas for each story (p.84-87), and use that as reference for the coding.]]></description><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/stein-&amp;-glenn_coding-schema.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Stein &amp; Glenn_Coding schema.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:27:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[SteinGlenn1979]]></title><link>narrative-models/2_story-grammar/1_stein-&amp;-glenn-1979/primary-source/steinglenn1979.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/2_Story grammar/1_Stein &amp; Glenn 1979/Primary source/SteinGlenn1979.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 14:22:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[gagarina-et-al2012_MAIN]]></title><link>narrative-models/5_main/gagarina-et-al2012_main.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/5_MAIN/gagarina-et-al2012_MAIN.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 14:22:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Schneider2006]]></title><link>narrative-models/4_enni/primary-source/schneider2006.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/4_ENNI/Primary source/Schneider2006.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 14:20:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[BermanSlobin1994]]></title><link>narrative-models/3_berman-&amp;-slobin-1994/primary-source/bermanslobin1994.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Narrative models/3_Berman &amp; Slobin 1994/Primary source/BermanSlobin1994.pdf</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 13:04:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>